<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ailearningloop</title>
<link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/</link>
<atom:link href="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Venturing Beyond My Roots: An AI Odyssey Unfolds for This Non-Tech Trailblazer!</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Mentorship Milestone: Q2 Certificates from DeepLearning.AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/q2-mentor-certs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m excited to share a milestone that reflects my commitment to giving back to the AI learning community.</p>
<p>Over the past quarter, I’ve had the privilege of serving as a <strong>Mentor</strong> in the <a href="https://www.deeplearning.ai">DeepLearning.AI</a> Discourse forums, supporting learners in their journey through two impactful specializations:</p>
<ul>
<li>🧠 <strong>Data Analytics Professional Certificate Specialization</strong></li>
<li>⚙️ <strong>TensorFlow Developer Professional Certificate Specialization</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>As someone who has benefited greatly from open learning communities, I know how transformative peer guidance can be. Mentoring gave me the chance to: - Clarify concepts for others (and often for myself!), - Share real-world insights on projects and tools, - And most importantly, connect with passionate, curious learners from all over the globe.</p>
<p>I’m honored to have received these <strong>Q2 2025 Mentor Participation Certificates</strong> in recognition of that work: <img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/q2-mentor-certs/DAG-Q2-mentor.png" class="img-fluid"> <img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/q2-mentor-certs/TF1-Q2-mentor.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I’m deeply thankful to the DeepLearning.AI team for creating such a thriving and inclusive space for learners and mentors alike.</p>
<p>Stay curious, stay generous.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>If you’re learning or mentoring in AI, feel free to reach out or share your experience—I’d love to hear your story!</em></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mentorship</category>
  <category>deepLearning.ai</category>
  <category>ai community</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/q2-mentor-certs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/q2-mentor-certs/DAG-Q2-mentor.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="111" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Announcing BioAid QA: A Multilingual Biomedical Assistant Backed by the Cohere Catalyst Grant</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/cohere-grant/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><em>“AI is only powerful if it reaches the people who need it most.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is with great pleasure that I announce to all that I’ve been selected as a <strong>Cohere Labs Catalyst Grant</strong> recipient!</p>
<p>This grant supports bold ideas that use large language models to tackle real-world problems. With Cohere’s support and $2,000 in API credits, I’m launching a project I deeply care about: <strong>BioAid QA</strong>, an open-source, multilingual biomedical question-answering assistant for underserved communities.</p>
<hr>
<section id="what-is-bioaid-qa" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-bioaid-qa">What is BioAid QA?</h2>
<p><strong>BioAid QA</strong> is a retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) assistant designed to help healthcare workers and patients access trustworthy medical information in <strong>English, Hausa, Swahili, and French</strong>.</p>
<p>It integrates <strong>Cohere’s Command, Embed, and Rerank</strong> models with a curated corpus of WHO and NIH resources. The system will be deployed via a lightweight <strong>Gradio</strong> interface and hosted on <strong>Hugging Face Spaces</strong>, making it accessible even in low-bandwidth settings.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="technical-overview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="technical-overview">Technical Overview</h2>
<p><strong>BioAid QA</strong> will be built as follows:</p>
<section id="document-ingestion-indexing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="document-ingestion-indexing">1. Document Ingestion &amp; Indexing</h3>
<ul>
<li>Curate biomedical texts (e.g., WHO guidelines, NIH fact sheets).</li>
<li>Split into passages and embed using <strong>Cohere Embed</strong>.</li>
<li>Store embeddings in a <strong>Chroma</strong> index.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="multilingual-retrieval-reranking" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="multilingual-retrieval-reranking">2. Multilingual Retrieval &amp; Reranking</h3>
<ul>
<li>User questions (in multiple languages) are embedded and matched via nearest-neighbor search.</li>
<li>Passages are reranked using <strong>Cohere Rerank</strong> for relevance.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="answer-generation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="answer-generation">3. Answer Generation</h3>
<ul>
<li>Top passages + query → <strong>Cohere Command</strong> → concise, fact-based answers.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="deployment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="deployment">4. Deployment</h3>
<ul>
<li>Gradio frontend with language toggles.</li>
<li>Client-side caching and optimized UX for slow networks.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="research-deliverables" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="research-deliverables">Research &amp; Deliverables</h2>
<p>This project doubles as software and a <strong>research contribution</strong>. The planned deliverables include:</p>
<ul>
<li>A <strong>peer-reviewed paper</strong> describing architecture, evaluation, and findings.</li>
<li>An MIT licensed <strong>open-source GitHub repo</strong></li>
<li><h2 id="a-deployed-app-on-hugging-face-spaces." class="anchored">A <strong>deployed app</strong> on Hugging Face Spaces.</h2></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="timeline-july-2025-january-2026" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="timeline-july-2025-january-2026">Timeline (July 2025 – January 2026)</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 14%">
<col style="width: 85%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Month</th>
<th>Milestone</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>July–August</td>
<td>Corpus curation, preprocessing, embedding &amp; indexing</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>September</td>
<td>Retrieval + rerank integration, validation with QA pairs</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>October</td>
<td>Command-based generation + accuracy evaluation</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>November</td>
<td>Refinement, paper drafts</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>December</td>
<td>Gradio app deployment + UX testing</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>January</td>
<td>Final paper submission + open-source release</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="thank-you-cohere-labs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thank-you-cohere-labs">Thank You, Cohere Labs</h2>
<p>Big thanks to <strong>Cohere Labs</strong> and the Catalyst team for supporting this project. I’m also grateful to the community at <a href="https://arewadatascience.github.io">Arewa Data Science Academy</a> for their continued encouragement.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="follow-along" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="follow-along">Follow Along</h2>
<p>I’ll be documenting the full journey — wins, failures, and findings — right here on my Quarto blog.</p>
<p>Stay tuned, and let’s build tools that <strong>make health knowledge accessible for everyone.</strong></p>
<p><em>— Lukman Aliyu</em><br>
<a href="mailto:lukman.j.aliyu@gmail.com">lukman.j.aliyu@gmail.com</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>cohere</category>
  <category>biomedical nlp</category>
  <category>biomedical-qa</category>
  <category>cohere labs</category>
  <category>catalyst</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/cohere-grant/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/cohere-grant/bio-aid-qa.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Leveling Up with CrewAI: My Multi-Agent Systems Journey with DeepLearning.AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/crewai-cert/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="leveling-up-with-crewai-my-multi-agent-systems-journey-with-deeplearning.ai" class="level1">
<h1>Leveling Up with CrewAI: My Multi-Agent Systems Journey with DeepLearning.AI</h1>
<section id="a-new-milestone" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-new-milestone">A New Milestone</h2>
<p>I’m excited to share that I’ve just earned my <strong>CrewAI badge</strong> after completing two hands-on courses from <strong>DeepLearning.AI</strong> on designing, deploying, and optimizing multi-agent AI systems.</p>
<p>This badge is a symbol of a new way of thinking: about how a <strong>team of AI agents</strong> can work together to solve complex problems.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/crewai-cert/crewai-badge.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>CrewAI Badge</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><em>Badge awarded by João Moura, Founder &amp; CEO of CrewAI</em></p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="what-i-learned-from-single-prompts-to-agentic-intelligence" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-i-learned-from-single-prompts-to-agentic-intelligence">What I Learned: From Single Prompts to Agentic Intelligence</h2>
<p>These courses taught me that while prompting a single LLM is powerful, orchestrating a <strong>crew of AI agents</strong> is revolutionary. Here’s a breakdown of what I learned:</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="course-1-multi-agent-systems-with-crewai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="course-1-multi-agent-systems-with-crewai">Course 1: <em>Multi-Agent Systems with CrewAI</em></h2>
<p>This foundational course helped me understand the <strong>core principles of multi-agent design</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Natural Language Agent Design</strong>: Define each agent’s role, goal, and backstory with simple prompts.</li>
<li><strong>Specialization &amp; Decomposition</strong>: Break complex workflows into manageable sub-tasks across a crew.</li>
<li><strong>Memory</strong>: Equip agents with short-term, long-term, and shared memory for context-aware performance.</li>
<li><strong>Guardrails</strong>: Handle hallucinations, infinite loops, and error recovery in a structured way.</li>
<li><strong>Cooperation Models</strong>: Sequence agents in parallel, series, or hierarchy for maximum effectiveness.</li>
</ul>
<section id="real-world-projects" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-world-projects">Real-World Projects:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Tailoring resumes and prepping for interviews<br>
</li>
<li>Researching and editing technical articles<br>
</li>
<li>Automating customer support<br>
</li>
<li>Running outreach campaigns<br>
</li>
<li>Planning events<br>
</li>
<li>Conducting financial analysis</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="course-2-practical-multi-ai-agents-advanced-use-cases" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="course-2-practical-multi-ai-agents-advanced-use-cases">Course 2: <em>Practical Multi AI Agents &amp; Advanced Use Cases</em></h2>
<p>This advanced course took things to the next level with <strong>real-world agentic applications</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Complex Workflows</strong>: Use nested crews and multi-agent orchestration for sophisticated systems.</li>
<li><strong>Tool Integration</strong>: Connect agents to web search, CRMs, data pipelines, and RAG systems.</li>
<li><strong>Performance Testing</strong>: Measure metrics, incorporate human feedback, and optimize results.</li>
<li><strong>Deployment Readiness</strong>: Build and test agent apps ready for real-world deployment.</li>
<li><strong>LLM Strategy</strong>: Use the right model (size, provider) for each agent’s task, leading to cost-effective AI applications.</li>
</ul>
<section id="use-cases-i-built" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="use-cases-i-built">Use Cases I Built:</h3>
<ul>
<li>A crew for automated project planning<br>
</li>
<li>Lead scoring with personalized email writing<br>
</li>
<li>Support ticket analysis with data visualization<br>
</li>
<li>A content crew using RAG + editors + social copy generators</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="relevance" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="relevance">Relevance</h2>
<p>We’re moving from single-model chatbots to <strong>modular AI ecosystems</strong>. These agentic systems mirror real-world teams that are specialized, autonomous, and collaborative.</p>
<p>With these skills, I can now build: - Business automation pipelines<br>
- Data-rich analysis tools<br>
- Content generation workflows<br>
- Scalable, intelligent assistants</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>
<p>These two courses have ignited a fire to build. I’m currently working on:</p>
<ul>
<li>Custom workflows using CrewAI and LangGraph<br>
</li>
<li>Experimenting with memory tools and parallel agents<br>
</li>
<li>Sharing demos and insights from my own agentic projects</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Special thanks to <strong>João Moura</strong> and <strong>DeepLearning.AI</strong> for creating such an empowering learning experience. If you’re curious about how agentic systems are shaping the future of AI, I’d love to connect, share, and collaborate.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>The future isn’t just AI-powered. It’s AI-teamed.</strong><br>
Let’s build it.</p>
</blockquote>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>crewai</category>
  <category>deepLearningai</category>
  <category>multi-agent systems</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/crewai-cert/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/crewai-cert/crewai-badge.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="102" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On Earning a Hackathon Certificate</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/agents-hackathon/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Participating in the Gradio Agents MCP Hackathon last month was an incredible experience. Thanks to generous API credits from providers like Mistral, OpenAI, Anthropic, and others, I found myself with nearly $400 worth of credits to explore. Drowning in so many APIs pushed me to experiment, learn, and grow as an AI developer.</p>
<p>I submitted two distinct projects to the competition. Although I didn’t win a prize, the process taught me invaluable lessons—from designing multi-agent workflows to integrating conversational tools with custom prompts. And best of all, I received a certificate recognizing my active participation and project submissions.</p>
<p>Receiving that certificate felt like a badge of honor. It reminds me that each hackathon is an opportunity not only to compete, but to sharpen my skills and connect with the community. I’m especially grateful to Hugging Face for organizing this event and supporting developers like me.</p>
<p>Next stop: Deep Learning Indaba! I’m confident that the insights and hands‑on experience I’ve gained will make me a stronger contender this year. In shāʾ Allāh, my winning time will come—I’ll keep building, learning, and participating.</p>
<p>Here’s a snapshot of my certificate:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/agents-hackathon/agents-cert.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>My Hackathon Certificate</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>agents</category>
  <category>gradio</category>
  <category>mcp</category>
  <category>hackathon</category>
  <category>hugging face</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/agents-hackathon/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/agents-hackathon/agents-cert.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="102" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring Power BI</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/power-bi/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Fifteen days ago, I hit a major personal milestone: a <strong>500-day streak</strong> on DataCamp. After immersing myself in AI-related courses for months, I decided to take a short detour to revisit a different domain—<strong>data analytics</strong>. So this week, I focused on completing the <a href="https://www.datacamp.com/completed/statement-of-accomplishment/track/12b5958754200636ba45352dc12c8007e8c5a30b">Power BI Fundamentals</a> track on DataCamp.</p>
<p>I sprinted through the track.After all, I’m no longer a novice in the data world. Having recently completed and even helped shape the <strong>DeepLearning.AI Data Analytics Professional Certificate</strong>, many of the foundational ideas were already familiar. This prior experience made the learning curve gentler and the journey much more exciting.</p>
<p>Admittedly, I had some initial concerns. Power BI is closed source, and using it outside the DataCamp environment required a Windows laptop, something I don’t use by default. But I reminded myself that the value of practical, hands-on knowledge far outweighs the constraints. And <em>alhamdulillah</em>, it paid off. The skills I gained are very likely to be transferable.</p>
<p>Now that I’ve completed the track, I’m setting my sights on the longer <strong>Data Analysis with Power BI</strong> track, and perhaps even the <strong>Microsoft certification</strong> eventually. Just like I hoped, diving deeper into Power BI gave me a firmer grasp of key data concepts. It was truly exhilarating.</p>
<p>I explored tools like <strong>Power Query</strong>, <strong>DAX (Data Analysis Expressions)</strong>, and became more comfortable navigating the Power BI interface. A standout experience was a full course centered around a <strong>customer churn</strong> case study. It gave me a solid, practical scenario to apply what I had learned and boosted my confidence in building analytics solutions.</p>
<p>Taking this short break from AI-focused learning reminded me how enriching it can be to return to the foundations. It gave me fresh data intuition and a renewed appreciation for the analytics process. I’m energized and looking forward to building on this momentum, and, in sha Allah, realizing even bigger dreams this year.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>datacamp</category>
  <category>data analytics</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/power-bi/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Yet Another Quarter of Dedicated Mentorship</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/deeplearning-mentorship/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am happy to announce to all that I have been recognized once again as one of the top contributing mentors for the two specializations I mentor at the DeepLearning.AI forum, the Data Analytics Professional Certification and the Tensorflow Developer Professional Certification. Here are the certifications</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/deeplearning-mentorship/data-analytics.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>data analytics</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/deeplearning-mentorship/tensorflow-dev.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>tensorflow developer</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Super grateful to <code>DeepLearning.AI</code> for granting me this wonderful opportunity.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <category>mentorship</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/deeplearning-mentorship/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/deeplearning-mentorship/data-analytics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="111" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Behind the Scenes: Testing the DeepLearning.AI Data Analytics Professional Certificate</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/data-analytics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m excited to share that I’ve been recognized as a Top Tester for the third course, Python for Data Analytics, in the new DeepLearning.AI Data Analytics Professional Certificate!</p>
<p>This marks my third Top Tester award in the specialization — having previously contributed to the development of the first two courses as well. With two more courses still ahead, the journey so far has been incredibly rewarding, both in contributing to the learner experience and strengthening my own skills along the way.</p>
<p>One aspect I deeply appreciate about this specialization is how thoughtfully it’s structured:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Courses 1 and 2 build a strong foundation in analytics fundamentals, starting with spreadsheets and data thinking.</p></li>
<li><p>Course 3 makes a natural transition into Python, giving learners practical, hands-on experience with real-world analytics projects — covering topics like retail sales trends, environmental data, and more.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>What makes the third course particularly special is its emphasis on realistic coding challenges. It doesn’t just walk you through polished examples; it encourages troubleshooting and critical thinking — skills that are essential for real-world analytics work.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, Courses 4 and 5 are set to dive even deeper into advanced analytics topics and tools, making this specialization an excellent pathway for anyone serious about becoming a data professional.</p>
<p>I’m also honored to have been recognized as a mentor for the course, thanks to the deep understanding I’ve developed through testing and feedback.</p>
<p>A huge thank you to the entire DeepLearning.AI team for the opportunity to contribute! If you’re looking to start or strengthen your career in data analytics, I highly recommend checking out this specialization. It’s been a fantastic learning experience, and I can’t wait to see what’s next!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <category>mentorship</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/data-analytics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 29 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/data-analytics/top-tester.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="111" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Celebrating Recognition from DeepLearning.AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/mentorship-recognition/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am thrilled to share that I have been recognized by DeepLearning.AI for my contributions and guidance as a mentor in for the TensorFlow Developer Professional Certificate Specialization in the DeepLearning.AI forum. This honor reflects my passion for empowering learners in the field of artificial intelligence and supporting their journeys toward mastering deep learning.</p>
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/mentorship-recognition/Lukman.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Certificate"> As a mentor, I’ve had the privilege of engaging with an incredible community of learners, offering insights, answering questions, and fostering collaboration. This recognition strengthens my commitment to knowledge sharing and the collective growth of AI enthusiasts worldwide.</p>
<p>I am grateful to DeepLearning.AI for the recognition and acknowledgment. Here’s to continuing to learn, teach, and contribute to the ever-evolving field of AI!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <category>mentorship</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/mentorship-recognition/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/mentorship-recognition/Lukman.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="111" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An Exploration of Geom-Stat Pairs in R Programming’s Tidyverse</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/geom-stats/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>R’s tidyverse has a rich visualization ecosystem that is exemplified by the popular ggplot2. In this article, I attempt to look at the different geoms and the stats linked to them.</p>
<p>Below is a list of common geom-stat pairs in ggplot2. Each pair consists of a geometric object (geom) and a statistical transformation (stat). They are closely associated because the geom specifies how the data is visually represented, while the stat determines how the data is processed before being passed to the geom.</p>
</section>
<section id="list-of-common-geom-stat-pairs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="list-of-common-geom-stat-pairs">List of Common Geom-Stat Pairs</h2>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 32%">
<col style="width: 28%">
<col style="width: 39%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Geom Function</th>
<th>Default Stat</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_bar()</td>
<td>stat_count</td>
<td>Creates bar charts by counting occurrences in raw data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_col()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Creates bar charts directly from precomputed data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_histogram()</td>
<td>stat_bin</td>
<td>Creates histograms by binning data into ranges.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_boxplot()</td>
<td>stat_boxplot</td>
<td>Creates box plots summarizing data with median and quartiles.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_density()</td>
<td>stat_density</td>
<td>Creates density plots by estimating the distribution curve.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_smooth()</td>
<td>stat_smooth</td>
<td>Adds a smoothed line (e.g., LOESS, linear) to the data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_point()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Plots points directly as provided in the data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_line()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Creates line plots directly from the data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_violin()</td>
<td>stat_ydensity</td>
<td>Creates violin plots showing the density distribution.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_pointrange()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Displays points with ranges using precomputed data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_ribbon()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Displays shaded areas between ranges (e.g., confidence bands).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_path()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Connects data points in order provided.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_tile()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Creates tiles (e.g., heatmaps) based on precomputed values.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_text()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Adds text annotations to the plot.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_sf()</td>
<td>stat_sf</td>
<td>Handles spatial data in simple features (SF) format.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_contour()</td>
<td>stat_contour</td>
<td>Plots contour lines based on 2D data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_map()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Displays map polygons or paths from preprocessed spatial data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_polygon()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Displays polygons (e.g., regions).</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_freqpoly()</td>
<td>stat_bin</td>
<td>Similar to a histogram, but displays frequencies as lines.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_bin2d()</td>
<td>stat_bin_2d</td>
<td>Bins 2D data into squares for heatmaps.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_hex()</td>
<td>stat_binhex</td>
<td>Bins 2D data into hexagons for hexbin plots.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_quantile()</td>
<td>stat_quantile</td>
<td>Adds quantile regression lines to the plot.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>geom_errorbar()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Displays error bars from precomputed summary data.</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>geom_segment()</td>
<td>stat_identity</td>
<td>Draws line segments using precomputed start and end points.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="what-do-these-pairs-have-in-common" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-do-these-pairs-have-in-common">What Do These Pairs Have in Common?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Division of Responsibility: The stat processes or summarizes the raw data (e.g., counting, binning, calculating densities, or smoothing). The geom visualizes the processed data (e.g., as bars, lines, points, or polygons).</li>
<li>Interchangeability: Most geoms can work with different stats and vice versa, though the defaults are designed for common use cases. For example, geom_bar() uses stat_count by default, but you can explicitly specify stat_identity for precomputed data.</li>
<li>Defaults:Each geom has a default stat, and vice versa. These defaults are chosen to match typical use cases (e.g., geom_histogram() defaults to stat_bin).</li>
<li>Input Data: Both geoms and stats rely on mappings defined in aes() to determine how variables in the dataset relate to the plot’s structure.</li>
<li>Customization:You can override the default behavior of either the geom or the stat to fit specific needs (e.g., applying a custom statistical transformation or using a different visualization).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Geom-stat pairs in ggplot2 represent a powerful abstraction where the stat transforms data, and the geom visualizes it. While defaults streamline common tasks, their flexibility allows users to mix and match geoms and stats for a wide variety of visualizations.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ggplot2</category>
  <category>tidyverse</category>
  <category>r-programming</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/geom-stats/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>On Being Featured by DeepLearning.AI: A Milestone in My AI Journey</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dlai-feature/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A significant milestone in my artificial intelligence journey recently materialized when DeepLearning.AI featured my story across their global platforms. The recognition came from a forum post where I shared my experiences as a course tester and mentor, reflecting on a journey that began in January 2023 with Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning Specialization.</p>
<section id="the-journey-to-recognition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-journey-to-recognition">The Journey to Recognition</h2>
<p>My involvement with DeepLearning.AI has been transformative. What started as enrolling in a single course evolved into a deep engagement with the AI community. As a course tester, I’ve had the privilege of providing feedback that helps shape the learning experience for future students. In my role as a mentor, I’ve guided numerous learners through the complexities of machine learning, witnessing their growth from novices to confident practitioners.</p>
</section>
<section id="global-reach-and-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="global-reach-and-impact">Global Reach and Impact</h2>
<p>The feature was shared across DeepLearning.AI’s extensive social media network:</p>
<ul>
<li>LinkedIn showcased my journey to their professional network of AI enthusiasts</li>
<li>X (formerly Twitter) broadcast my story to the global tech community</li>
<li>Facebook reached aspiring AI practitioners worldwide</li>
<li>Instagram captured the visual narrative of my path in AI</li>
</ul>
<p>A particularly touching moment came when my friend Abbas shared the Instagram feature with me—a reminder of how supportive the tech community can be.</p>
</section>
<section id="professional-growth-and-future-aspirations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="professional-growth-and-future-aspirations">Professional Growth and Future Aspirations</h2>
<p>This recognition arrives at a pivotal moment in my career. After three enriching years at Zipline, where I applied AI to revolutionize medical delivery systems in Africa, I’m preparing for new challenges. My experience has reinforced my belief in AI’s potential to transform healthcare delivery in developing regions. The intersection of my pharmaceutical background with artificial intelligence has positioned me uniquely in the healthcare-tech space. At Zipline, I’ve witnessed firsthand how AI can optimize medical supply chains and improve access to healthcare in remote areas.</p>
</section>
<section id="community-impact-and-mentorship" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-impact-and-mentorship">Community Impact and Mentorship</h2>
<p>One of my proudest achievements has been mentoring in the AI community. Through DeepLearning.AI’s platform, I’ve had the opportunity to: - Guide aspiring data scientists through complex concepts - Share practical insights from real-world AI applications - Build a supportive network of learners and practitioners - Contribute to making AI education more accessible</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>This recognition from DeepLearning.AI has reinforced my commitment to advancing AI education and application in healthcare. As I prepare for the next chapter in my career, I remain dedicated to: - Continuing to mentor and support aspiring AI practitioners - Contributing to the development of AI solutions in healthcare - Building bridges between technology and healthcare delivery - Advancing AI education in Africa</p>
</section>
<section id="social-media-links" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="social-media-links">Social Media Links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://x.com/DeepLearningAI/status/1853618233384878573">View on X (Twitter)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/deeplearningai_an-inspiring-journey-from-nigeria-see-how-activity-7259383961997475840-BGqC">Read on LinkedIn</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/1CsDcrJucT/">Facebook Post</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/deeplearningai/p/DB-N2SPM9fO/">Instagram Feature</a></li>
</ul>
<p>In sha Allah, this milestone marks just the beginning of greater achievements to come. I’m deeply grateful for the support of my community, mentors, and colleagues who have been part of this journey. As we continue to push the boundaries of what’s possible with AI, I look forward to contributing to more innovations that make a real difference in people’s lives.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <category>career-milestone</category>
  <category>ai-education</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dlai-feature/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Completing the Analyzing Genomic Data in R track on DataCamp</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/genomic-data-analysis/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I just completed DataCamp’s “Analyzing Genomic Data in R” track, which was an incredible dive into using R and Bioconductor for genomic analysis. This track had four in-depth courses that helped me build skills for analyzing genomic datasets:</p>
<ul>
<li>Introduction to Bioconductor in R</li>
<li>RNA-Seq with Bioconductor in R</li>
<li>Differential Expression Analysis with limma in R</li>
<li>ChIP-seq with Bioconductor in R</li>
</ul>
<p>In this post, I’ll briefly walk you through each course and share what I learned and why it was so exciting.</p>
<section id="introduction-to-bioconductor-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-to-bioconductor-in-r">Introduction to Bioconductor in R</h2>
<p>This course was my gateway to Bioconductor—an essential resource for genomic analysis in R. I learned how to install packages with the BiocInstaller, work with different types of genomic data, and explore real-life datasets like those for fungi, viruses, and even plants. Tools like BioStrings, GenomicRanges, and ShortRead made manipulating and filtering raw data surprisingly accessible.</p>
<p>One highlight was learning to use built-in datasets (BSgenome and TxDb) and apply functions to search for patterns in genomic sequences. Quality control was another important aspect, using ShortRead and Rqc to ensure that my data was clean and usable—a crucial step in genomic research.</p>
</section>
<section id="rna-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rna-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r">RNA-Seq with Bioconductor in R</h2>
<p>In this course, I got hands-on with RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) data, focusing on differential expression analysis—identifying genes that express differently between experimental conditions. I used DESeq2 to analyze gene expression between fibrosis and normal samples, which was a powerful introduction to understanding biological significance in genomics.</p>
<p>An interesting takeaway was the reminder that data interpretation doesn’t stop at identifying significant genes. I learned that experimental validation is key—around 5% of “significant” results are false positives, and ensuring that our findings are accurate requires lab-based verification. Additionally, I explored how functional analysis can help us see the biological meaning behind the data by identifying enriched processes or pathways.</p>
</section>
<section id="differential-expression-analysis-with-limma-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="differential-expression-analysis-with-limma-in-r">Differential Expression Analysis with limma in R</h2>
<p>This course added another layer to my understanding of differential expression—specifically using limma, a versatile and widely-used Bioconductor package. I visualized gene expression levels with plotDensities and normalized raw data to ensure reliable analysis. One key aspect was principal component analysis (plotMDS), which helped me see whether data variation matched my experimental variables or if there were other technical factors at play.</p>
<p>I also learned to identify important genes using volcano plots and assess results using p-value distributions. The course highlighted how essential quality control is, emphasizing the need for careful examination to avoid misleading conclusions. Wrapping up, I conducted gene set enrichment analysis to explore biological pathways using KEGG and Gene Ontology databases—this really helped broaden my perspective from individual genes to broader biological systems.</p>
</section>
<section id="chip-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chip-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r">ChIP-seq with Bioconductor in R</h2>
<p>ChIP-seq (Chromatin Immunoprecipitation Sequencing) was the final frontier in this track, and it was challenging but incredibly rewarding. I learned to import ChIP-seq data using rtracklayer and GenomicAlignments, visualize it with Gviz, and ensure its quality by dealing with repetitive regions through blacklisting and QC reports with ChIPQC.</p>
<p>The analysis culminated in using DiffBind to identify differentially bound peaks and create heatmaps and PCA plots to understand sample clustering. Finally, I used the chipenrich package to link peaks to nearby genes and performed enrichment analysis to see which biological processes were associated with these binding events. This part of the course really helped tie everything together and made me confident about analyzing real-world ChIP-seq data.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-on-the-journey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-the-journey">Reflections on the Journey</h2>
<p>Completing this track gave me practical skills to handle various genomic datasets and analyze them meaningfully. Each course built on the previous one, reinforcing core concepts while adding new techniques, ultimately providing a well-rounded introduction to genomic analysis in R.</p>
<p>My next step is to apply what I’ve learned to real datasets—perhaps even contribute to open research initiatives. Bioconductor’s community and support forums will be great allies as I dive deeper into genomics. As I am seriously considering grad school, this is a skill that will help me immensely in the pursuit of my goals.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/genomic-data-analysis/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/genomic-data-analysis/genomic-analysis.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="83" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Completing the Health Informatics Specialization on Coursera</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/health-informatics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am excited to announce that I have completed the Health Informatics Specialization offered by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera. This learning journey, which began in November while I was in Rwanda, has taken me across different geographies—from Kaduna to Ogoja in Cross River State, and even to Senegal—and has finally concluded in Nigeria.</p>
<p>The specialization was a deep dive into the world of Health Informatics, offering a comprehensive understanding of both the social and technical dimensions of the field. It comprised five meticulously curated courses, each providing unique insights and knowledge essential for anyone interested in the intersection of healthcare and information technology.</p>
<p>The Social and Technical Context of Health Informatics: This course laid the foundation, exploring the broader contexts in which health informatics operates. It helped me appreciate the complexities involved in integrating technology into healthcare systems, especially in low-resource settings.</p>
<p>Leading Change in Health Informatics: This was my favorite course, expertly taught by Dr.&nbsp;Ashwini Davison. It resonated deeply with me as it discussed the challenges and strategies for implementing change in healthcare systems—a critical issue for countries like Nigeria, where the adoption of electronic health records (EHRs) is still in its infancy. The course provided practical frameworks and tools for driving change, which I found incredibly valuable.</p>
<p>The Outcomes and Interventions of Health Informatics: This course offered a deep understanding of the types of interventions that can be made using health informatics and how to measure their outcomes. It provided insights into how data can be leveraged to drive decision-making and improve patient care.</p>
<p>The Data Science of Health Informatics: As someone who has been delving into data science for a while, this course was a perfect blend of my interests. It covered critical data science concepts and techniques relevant to health informatics, enhancing my ability to analyze and interpret complex health data.</p>
<p>Culminating Project in Health Informatics: The final course brought everything together with a project-based approach. We were tasked with analyzing a real-world scenario involving ImprovingHealth, a non-profit healthcare organization facing challenges in implementing systematic Health-Related Social Needs (HRSN) screenings across its clinics. The project highlighted the inefficiencies in paper-based data collection methods and the lack of adequate staff training and buy-in, which were significant barriers to identifying and addressing social determinants of health for Medicare beneficiaries.</p>
<p>Reflecting on this journey, I realize how far-reaching the impact of health informatics can be, particularly in enhancing healthcare delivery and improving patient outcomes. The specialization has equipped me with the knowledge and skills to better understand and tackle the challenges in this field, especially in regions where healthcare systems face significant technological and infrastructural barriers.</p>
<p>I look forward to applying these insights and continuing to contribute to the evolution of digital health and health informatics in meaningful ways. I am especially excited about the potential for collaboration and innovation that lies ahead.</p>
<p>Thank you to all the instructors and fellow learners who made this journey enriching and rewarding!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates on my journey into health informatics and how we can leverage data for better health outcomes. 🚀</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>informatics</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/health-informatics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/health-informatics/health-informatics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="92" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024 Day 6: A Journey Through Inspiring Workshops and Innovation in Health AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s hard to believe that we’re already at Day 6 of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024! Time seems to have flown by, and it’s incredible to think that there’s only one more day left. The Indaba has been a whirlwind of knowledge, networking, and inspiration. Today was a day dedicated to workshops, and the challenge was real: so many fascinating topics were on the table, but they all ran simultaneously!</p>
<p>The workshops available today were diverse and compelling, each catering to different facets of AI and machine learning in Africa. Here’s a glimpse of the workshops I had to choose from:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Weakly Supervised Computer Vision Workshop: Exploring techniques that allow models to learn from limited labeled data, a crucial need in regions where data labeling is resource-intensive.</p></li>
<li><p>The NeuroAI Workshop: Bridging neuroscience and AI, focusing on how principles from the brain can be applied to AI systems, and vice versa.</p></li>
<li><p>Empowering African Voices in AI: A discussion on inclusivity and the importance of representation in AI, promoting diversity of thought and experience.</p></li>
<li><p>Voices of Africa: Building the Infrastructure for African NLP: This workshop focused on developing natural language processing (NLP) tools and datasets that reflect the diversity of African languages, essential for creating inclusive AI applications.</p></li>
<li><p>AfriClimateAI - Uniting for Climate-Resilient Africa: Bringing together experts and practitioners to discuss the role of AI in tackling climate change in Africa, fostering data and knowledge exchange to build a more climate-resilient future.</p></li>
<li><p>Robot Learning for Africa Workshop: Delving into how robotics and machine learning can be leveraged for various applications in the African context, from agriculture to healthcare.</p></li>
<li><p>Data Science for Health in Africa Workshop: Organized by Sisonke Biotik and Ro’ya, two grassroots communities focused on Machine Learning and Global Health in Africa, this workshop looked at innovative approaches to using data science in healthcare.</p></li>
<li><p>AI for Good Symposium in Africa: Highlighting projects and research that use AI to address pressing social issues and contribute to sustainable development across the continent.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>With so many great choices, it was difficult to decide, but ultimately, my interest in the intersection of AI and health led me to attend the Data Science for Health in Africa workshop.</p>
<section id="diving-deep-into-ai-for-health-in-africa" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diving-deep-into-ai-for-health-in-africa">Diving Deep into AI for Health in Africa</h2>
<p>The workshop, jointly organized by Sisonke Biotik and Ro’ya, was a hub of activity and collaboration. Both organizations are grassroots, participatory communities focused on advancing Machine Learning and Global Health in Africa. The sessions were highly interactive, and the atmosphere was one of shared learning and innovation.</p>
<p>We started with a practical workshop on using R for health data algorithms, which was particularly valuable for practitioners and researchers interested in leveraging open-source tools for health analytics. It was a hands-on session that allowed participants to get acquainted with different techniques and tools for analyzing complex health datasets.</p>
</section>
<section id="insights-from-ai-pioneers-in-health" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-from-ai-pioneers-in-health">Insights from AI Pioneers in Health</h2>
<p>The workshop featured a range of insightful presentations. Among the highlights were:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Muhammad Al-Fatih’s Presentation on SKAI: SKAI (Satellite Knowledge Augmented Intelligence) is an innovative platform that utilizes AI and satellite imagery to provide real-time insights and actionable intelligence. This is particularly crucial for effective decision-making during disaster response, where timely information can save lives. Muhammad walked us through how SKAI integrates different data sources and uses AI to analyze satellite imagery, making it a game-changer for disaster management and emergency response in Africa.</p></li>
<li><p>Mercy Asiedu’s Talk on Multifaceted Approaches to AI for Health in Africa: Mercy’s presentation was a deep dive into the multiple ways AI can be leveraged for health in Africa. She touched on the importance of benchmark datasets for health on the continent, noting that these datasets must reflect the diverse population to be truly impactful. The talk also covered innovative AI solutions that address specific health challenges in Africa, emphasizing the need for culturally and contextually relevant technologies.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="collaborative-innovation-pitching-ideas-to-revolutionize-healthcare" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborative-innovation-pitching-ideas-to-revolutionize-healthcare">Collaborative Innovation: Pitching Ideas to Revolutionize Healthcare</h2>
<p>One of the most exciting parts of the day was a collaborative session where participants were grouped together to pitch an idea that could potentially revolutionize healthcare in Africa. This was a fantastic opportunity to brainstorm and exchange ideas with people from diverse backgrounds, ranging from data scientists to healthcare professionals. The energy in the room was palpable, and the ideas that came out of these discussions were both creative and practical.</p>
</section>
<section id="speed-presentations-and-ideathon-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speed-presentations-and-ideathon-results">Speed Presentations and Ideathon Results</h2>
<p>To add to the excitement, there was a speed presentation competition where participants had a few minutes to present their innovative ideas or research findings. This fast-paced format was engaging and showcased the breadth of talent and creativity present at the Indaba.</p>
<p>Additionally, the results of the Ideathon, which was held a day earlier, were announced today. My team, NextGen Health Innovators, was thrilled to be awarded third place! We were recognized for our innovative solution aimed at improving vaccine delivery through AI and data science. Receiving our certificate and prize was a moment of pride and joy, capping off what has been an incredible day of learning and collaboration.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-and-looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-and-looking-ahead">Reflections and Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>Reflecting on today, I can confidently say it has been my best day at the Indaba so far. The workshops were about learning and connecting with like-minded individuals, exchanging ideas, and envisioning a future where AI can truly make a difference in healthcare across Africa. It was a day filled with inspiration, and it reinforced my belief in the power of collaboration and innovation.</p>
<p>It’s a bit bittersweet to realize that the Indaba is almost over. Tomorrow marks the final day, and while I’m looking forward to what it has in store, I can’t help but feel a little nostalgic already. The Deep Learning Indaba has been more than just a conference; it’s been a journey of growth, learning, and connection.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-06/lukman-dakar.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflecting on the Final Day of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024: A Journey of Insights and Inspiration</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As the saying goes, every beginning has an end, and the final day of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024 marked the conclusion of a week filled with knowledge-sharing, networking, and inspiration. This year’s Indaba was a true testament to the diversity and depth of AI conversations shaping Africa’s future. The final day was no exception, featuring several concurrent half-day workshops that challenged us to choose just one path to follow!</p>
<p>The workshop options were diverse, each promising to delve into a unique aspect of AI and its potential impact:</p>
<ul>
<li>Envisioning Humans in a Safe, AI Future</li>
<li>GeoAI for a Sustainable Future in Africa</li>
<li>Empowering Africa’s AI Future through High Performance and Cloud Computing</li>
<li>AI Regulation in Africa: Rationale, Considerations, and Way Forward</li>
</ul>
<p>I opted for the “Envisioning Humans in a Safe, AI Future” workshop, a choice that proved to be the right one for me. However, I must admit it was a tough call—each workshop offered something valuable, and it was unfortunate that I couldn’t attend them all. Alas, one can only be in one place at a time!</p>
<p>The workshop began with an introduction to ML Commons, an open initiative that aims to accelerate machine learning research, and ways to get involved. This set the stage for the discussions that followed, starting with a panel discussion on “Seeking Safer Spaces with AI Tools.” The panelists brought forward intriguing perspectives on how we can create AI tools that foster safer and more inclusive environments. The discussions were not only thought-provoking but also a call to action for all of us in the AI community.</p>
<p>Following the panel, we moved on to a segment titled “Behind the Research: Author Insights.” This session provided a deeper look into the journeys and motivations of researchers working at the intersection of AI and social good. It was inspiring to hear firsthand about the challenges they faced, the breakthroughs they achieved, and the lessons they learned along the way.</p>
<p>The workshop wrapped up with some final announcements and reflections on the discussions held throughout the day. As a token of appreciation for our engagement in this packed and event-studded session, all participants received certificates of attendance—a wonderful keepsake to remember this enriching experience.</p>
<p>After the workshops, the Wangari Maathai Impact Award was presented to Grace Muthoni for her groundbreaking research. Her work stood out among many, and it was heartening to see such talent being recognized and celebrated. Congratulations to Grace!</p>
<p>The day then transitioned into the final Indaba panel discussion, which served as a comprehensive summary of the entire event. The panel, composed of notable experts and thought leaders, tackled critical themes such as the need for skilling, foundational research, and the concept of human-in-the-loop AI—all while emphasizing the importance of not losing our unique identities as we navigate the evolving AI landscape.</p>
<p>One of the most compelling parts of the discussion was the exploration of future research directions, including the relationship between language and machine learning education, and AI’s potential role in tackling climate change. It was an important reminder that while it’s easy to get caught up in trending topics, our research should be driven by genuine curiosity and the unique challenges we wish to solve.</p>
<p>A major takeaway from the panel was the affirmation that our experiences are uniquely ours and that they are a valuable asset in shaping our paths in AI. No one else can walk our path for us, and leveraging our unique backgrounds and perspectives can lead to innovative and impactful contributions to the field.</p>
<p>Throughout the week, I’ve been sharing my experiences from Indaba, as encouraged, and it has been truly inspiring to see the passion and commitment of AI practitioners across the continent.</p>
<p>The final day concluded with a vibrant closing ceremony, where prizes were awarded to deserving winners, followed by a celebratory closing party that was filled with joy, music, and a sense of accomplishment. With that, Deep Learning Indaba 2024 came to a close.</p>
<p>But this isn’t goodbye—it’s simply “see you next year.” The next Indaba will be held in Kigali, Rwanda, and I’m already looking forward to the incredible conversations and experiences that await us there.</p>
<p>Stay tuned, and see you in Kigali next year!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024:Day 5, A Day of Insights, Innovation, and Inspiration</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Day 5 of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024 was filled with moments that highlighted the vibrancy and depth of AI research and innovation happening across Africa. The day began with a celebration of academic excellence as Fiskani Banda received the Grace Alele-Williams Masters Award for her outstanding master’s thesis. Her dedication to pushing the boundaries of knowledge is a true inspiration for all of us in the AI community.</p>
<p>Following this uplifting moment, we moved into a thought-provoking keynote by Dr.&nbsp;Judy Gichoya, Associate Professor of Radiology and Informatics at Emory University. Dr.&nbsp;Gichoya’s presentation, “Shortcuts Causing Bias in Medical Imaging,” was a deep dive into the often-overlooked issue of shortcut learning in AI. She skillfully unpacked how biases can stem from both dataset limitations and the nature of discriminative learning itself. This session resonated with me profoundly, particularly given my interest in the intersection of AI and health. It served as a powerful reminder of the need for transparency and understanding in AI models, especially when they are applied to critical fields like healthcare where biases can have real-world consequences.</p>
<p>The day’s agenda then shifted to a series of research showcases, demonstrating the diverse and impactful AI work being done across the continent. From using pre-trained models for essay scoring to flood prediction models and innovative approaches to predicting and preventing farmer-herder conflicts, the research presentations covered a wide array of domains. Each project underscored the potential of AI to address both local and global challenges, reaffirming the importance of inclusive and context-aware AI development.</p>
<p>I also had the opportunity to attend the Data Science for Health Ideathon. This was a dynamic and engaging session that brought together bright minds to brainstorm and propose innovative AI solutions for health challenges in Africa. The creativity and passion in the room were palpable, making it one of the most energizing parts of the day.</p>
<p>The afternoon featured a panel discussion and presentations from African startups, many of which are harnessing AI to tackle pressing issues on the continent. It’s always inspiring to see how these emerging companies are pushing the envelope and driving impact through AI.</p>
<p>Another significant session was the Faculty Engagement discussion, a first at Indaba. Faculty members from universities across Africa and beyond came together to share insights, challenges, and solutions for advancing AI education and research on the continent. It was a meaningful conversation, and I’m excited to hear that this will be a recurring feature at future Indabas.</p>
<p>Between sessions, I made sure to network with other attendees, exchanging ideas and learning about their work. I also visited the booths of various Indaba partners, gaining a deeper understanding of the incredible projects and initiatives they are supporting.</p>
<p>As the day concluded, I found myself reflecting on how each day at the Indaba seems to surpass the last. The experiences, the learning, and the connections all continue to make this journey incredibly rewarding. I can’t wait to see what the next days have in store!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates from Deep Learning Indaba 2024!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024:Day 4, Celebrating African Research, Learning, and Community Building</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-04/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today at Deep Learning Indaba 2024 was nothing short of inspiring! As the event unfolds, I’m continually amazed by the depth and diversity of research being conducted across Africa. Here’s a recap of my fourth day:</p>
<p><strong>Celebrating African Research Excellence</strong>: The day began with the Indaba Kambule Doctoral Thesis Award ceremony, which recognizes outstanding doctoral research by African scholars. This award is a testament to the originality and impact of research emerging from the continent, highlighting the innovative spirit driving Africa forward in AI and data science.</p>
<p><strong>Diving into Oral Presentations and Poster Sessions</strong>: The day continued with IndabaX Oral Presentations and two sessions of Poster Presentations. The posters showcased a range of exciting research:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deep Learning-Based Lesion Segmentation for Early Liver Tumor Detection in Rwanda: Using a hybrid ResNet-UNet model, researchers presented significant results in early tumor detection from liver CT scans—a major step forward for healthcare in Rwanda.</li>
<li>siSwatiSent: Sentiment Analysis Dataset for siSwati: A unique sentiment analysis dataset for the siSwati language, extracted from YouTube comments. This study emphasizes the need for more African language resources in NLP.</li>
<li>CHOWNET-V1: An Image Dataset of Nigerian Food: A fascinating dataset that addresses the underrepresentation of African cuisine in machine learning research, enhancing diversity in food classification tasks.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Mentorship and Knowledge Sharing</strong>: I was fortunate to join a mentorship session with Georgina Curto Rex. Our discussion revolved around the importance of selecting meaningful problems to work on and the role of having a guiding purpose as we explore various research avenues. This session was a reminder that our work should always aim to make a real-world impact.</p>
<p><strong>Understanding the Limitations of LLMs</strong>: The keynote lecture by Caglar Gulcehre focused on the limitations of large language models (LLMs). It was an eye-opening discussion that explored both the capabilities and the constraints of these models, sparking ideas on how we might improve and innovate further in the field.</p>
<p><strong>Learning to Publish</strong>: The day wrapped up with a Research Writing event, where we were taught the nuances of writing and publishing impactful research papers. This session was invaluable for anyone looking to contribute meaningfully to the academic community.</p>
<p><strong>A Memorable Arewa Data Science Connect</strong>: The day ended on a high note with our Arewa Data Science connect session. It was heartwarming to take a picture with my fellow Arewa Data Science folks at Indaba—strengthening our sense of community and shared purpose in advancing data science across Africa.</p>
<p><strong>A New Discovery</strong>: On a lighter note, I discovered a new country today—Eswatini! It was a humbling moment, reminding me of the endless learning opportunities that events like this bring.</p>
<p><strong>Reflecting on the Day</strong>: Today was a blend of knowledge, mentorship, and community. I feel incredibly fortunate to be part of this transformative event that is shaping the future of AI and data science in Africa. Here’s to more learning, connecting, and growing together!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates from Deep Learning Indaba 2024!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-04/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-04/arewadsdli.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024:Day 3, A Day of Insights, Innovation, and Inspiration</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Attending the Deep Learning Indaba 2024 in Dakar has been a whirlwind of learning, networking, and inspiration. Day 3 was particularly packed with enriching activities and thought-provoking sessions that left me energized and inspired.</p>
<p>The day began with a compelling keynote by Samy Bengio on “Learning to Reason.” Samy delved deep into the challenges that transformer models still face when it comes to reasoning. While transformers have revolutionized natural language processing, their ability to reason like humans remains limited. Samy presented some innovative methods to enhance this reasoning ability, sparking a lively discussion among attendees. It was fascinating to see how research continues to push the boundaries of what AI can achieve.</p>
<p>After the keynote, I attended a hands-on practical session on Federated Learning. Having spent the last two days tutoring, it was refreshing to be on the learning side again. We explored how federated learning can play a crucial role in fostering responsible AI, particularly by ensuring data privacy and security. We also got hands-on with Flower, an open-source framework for building federated learning systems, and discussed the added complexities that arise when working with heterogeneous datasets. Thanks to my prior experience with the DeepLearning.AI Federated Learning short course, I could dive deeper into the challenges and opportunities in this space.</p>
<p>Next, I joined a career mentorship session with Sekou Remy from IBM. This was one of the highlights of my day, as Sekou shared invaluable advice on navigating one’s career in AI. Some key takeaways included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Make decisions based on the evidence you can gather while planning your future.</li>
<li>Take advantage of internships during undergrad and grad school; they are invaluable for gaining experience.</li>
<li>Find a balance between acquiring new knowledge (exploration) and applying what you know (exploitation).</li>
<li>Time is your most valuable asset—use it wisely.</li>
<li>AI offers significant potential in data capture and analysis.</li>
<li>Always keep an open mind and be willing to learn.</li>
<li>Networking is not just a buzzword; it is key to professional growth.</li>
</ul>
<p>This session was a reminder of the importance of being strategic, adaptable, and proactive in our career journeys.</p>
<p>After that, I attended a fascinating session on “Multimodal Perception for Human and Animal Behavior Understanding,” led by Marwa Mahmoud from the University of Glasgow’s Behavioural AI Laboratory. Marwa discussed her work on the early detection of neurodevelopmental conditions in children using multimodal features, highlighting the critical need for explainable and interpretable models. Given that these models are designed to assist healthcare providers, transparency in AI decisions is paramount. She also touched on the use of probabilistic models as a first line of support in decision-making.</p>
<p>What struck me was the complexity and subjectivity involved in applying AI to psychology and behavior analysis, where getting well-labeled datasets can be incredibly challenging. Marwa also provided a glimpse into her work on modeling animal behavior, which can be even more daunting than human behavior. She referenced her paper, “Going Deeper than Tracking: A Survey of Computer Vision-Based Recognition of Animal Pain and Affective States,” which further explores these complexities.</p>
<p>To wrap up the day, I joined discussions on community programs, featuring inspiring talks from various AI communities like GhanaAI, Masakhane, and others. They shared their initiatives and the tangible impacts they’ve made in their regions. It was a powerful reminder of the importance of community in driving AI forward, especially in underrepresented regions. The discussions were filled with passion and a shared vision of using AI for good.</p>
<p>Throughout the day, I also had the opportunity to network with fellow attendees, exchange ideas, and work on our hackathon submission. The energy and camaraderie in the room were palpable, and it was exciting to be part of a community so dedicated to pushing the boundaries of AI.</p>
<p>Day 3 at Deep Learning Indaba 2024 was truly a day of insights, innovation, and inspiration—a perfect blend of learning, sharing, and growing together. I am looking forward to what the rest of the week will bring!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Day 2 at Deep Learning Indaba 2024: Bridging AI Innovation and Ethics in Africa</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As the sun rose over Dakar, Senegal, it marked the beginning of another exhilarating day at the Deep Learning Indaba 2024. Hosted by the prestigious Université Amadou Mahtar Mbow, this gathering of brilliant minds from across Africa continues to push the boundaries of AI innovation on the continent. Today’s experiences were nothing short of transformative, blending cutting-edge technology with ethical considerations and a spirit of collaboration that defines the African AI community.</p>
<section id="morning-keynote-causethical-ml---from-theory-to-practice" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="morning-keynote-causethical-ml---from-theory-to-practice">Morning Keynote: Causethical ML - From Theory to Practice</h2>
<p>The day kicked off with an enlightening keynote on Causethical Machine Learning. This session delved into the critical intersection of causal inference and ethical AI, emphasizing a fundamental principle: algorithms should not only be efficient but also fair and grounded in ethically acceptable reasoning.</p>
<p>The speaker articulated a compelling vision where fairness in AI isn’t just a moral imperative but a practical one. By ensuring that our algorithms make decisions based on ethically sound principles, we create a win-win scenario. Not only do we uphold justice and equality, but we also create systems that benefit all stakeholders in the long run. This approach to AI development resonates deeply with the African context, where technology must be developed with a keen awareness of diverse societal needs and historical inequities.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-for-good-microsofts-vision-for-positive-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-for-good-microsofts-vision-for-positive-impact">AI for Good: Microsoft’s Vision for Positive Impact</h2>
<p>Following the keynote, we had the privilege of hearing from representatives of the Microsoft AI for Good Research Lab. Their presentation was a testament to the transformative power of AI when applied to pressing global challenges.</p>
</section>
<section id="pushing-boundaries-snake-venom-analysis-using-large-language-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pushing-boundaries-snake-venom-analysis-using-large-language-models">Pushing Boundaries: Snake Venom Analysis Using Large Language Models</h2>
<p>One of the most fascinating sessions of the day focused on an unexpected application of AI: analyzing and sequencing snake venom using Large Language Models (LLMs). This presentation was a perfect example of how AI can revolutionize even the most specialized scientific fields. The researchers demonstrated how they’ve adapted LLMs, typically used for processing human languages, to “read” the complex molecular structures of various snake venoms. This application has enormous potential for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Accelerating the development of antivenoms</li>
<li>Identifying new compounds for pharmaceutical research</li>
<li>Enhancing our understanding of snake biology and evolution</li>
</ul>
<p>As someone deeply interested in both AI and biodiversity, I found this session to be a brilliant demonstration of interdisciplinary research. It showcased how AI tools developed for one domain can find groundbreaking applications in entirely different fields.</p>
</section>
<section id="hands-on-learning-tutoring-responsible-ai-practicals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hands-on-learning-tutoring-responsible-ai-practicals">Hands-on Learning: Tutoring Responsible AI Practicals</h2>
<p>A personal highlight of my day was the opportunity to serve as a tutor for the Responsible AI practicals. Having reviewed the notebooks ahead of the Indaba, I was excited to guide participants through the intricacies of developing AI systems with ethical considerations at their core. The notebooks (English and French) are available on <a href="https://github.com/deep-learning-indaba/indaba-pracs-2024/tree/main/practicals/Responsible_AI">github</a></p>
<p>What struck me most was the eagerness of the participants to engage with these critical issues. Their questions and insights reflected a deep understanding of the potential impacts of AI on African societies and a commitment to developing technologies that uplift rather than marginalize.</p>
<p>These sessions embodied the Indaba’s theme of “Xam Xamlé” – to gain knowledge and share it. The collaborative spirit in the room was palpable, with participants from various countries sharing their unique perspectives on responsible AI development.</p>
</section>
<section id="inspiring-vision-building-up-the-future-of-ai-in-africa" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="inspiring-vision-building-up-the-future-of-ai-in-africa">Inspiring Vision: Building Up the Future of AI in Africa</h2>
<p>The day concluded with an electrifying presentation by Karim Beguir titled “Building Up the Future of AI in Africa.” Beguir’s talk was a rallying cry for African AI researchers and developers, emphasizing that we are living in an unprecedented era of opportunity.</p>
<p>Key points from his presentation included:</p>
<ul>
<li>The democratization of AI tools, with resources like Llama 3.1 now accessible to researchers across the continent</li>
<li>The groundbreaking work being done at InstaDeep, showcasing African-led innovation in AI</li>
<li>An overview of Project Tatooine, a collaboration with GoMyCode aimed at nurturing the next generation of AI talent in Africa, particularly in less developed locations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Beguir’s central message</strong> – that “agents are the future” – sparked intense discussions among attendees. The vision of AI agents autonomously solving complex problems, tailored to African contexts, opened up exciting possibilities for innovation across various sectors.</p>
</section>
<section id="networking-and-collaboration-the-heart-of-indaba" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="networking-and-collaboration-the-heart-of-indaba">Networking and Collaboration: The Heart of Indaba</h2>
<p>While the formal sessions were incredibly informative, some of the most valuable moments came from the connections made between sessions. The Indaba’s atmosphere encourages spontaneous discussions and collaborations, leading to some exciting developments:</p>
<p>I joined two hackathons – one hosted by Meta and another by InstaDeep. These events are not just competitions but incubators for ideas that could evolve into impactful projects.</p>
<p>The coffee breaks buzzed with energy as participants exchanged ideas, formed impromptu working groups, and planned future collaborations.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-moment-of-personal-connection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-moment-of-personal-connection">A Moment of Personal Connection</h2>
<p>Amidst the whirlwind of activities, I experienced a deeply meaningful personal moment. After nearly two years of virtual collaboration, I finally met Dr.&nbsp;Shamsuddeen Hassan Muhammad in person. Our work together has been a source of immense learning and growth for me, and meeting face-to-face was an emotional and inspiring experience.</p>
<p>I also had the pleasure of meeting Dr.&nbsp;Idris Abdulmumin, another mentor who has played a crucial role in my journey. Having collaborated on a paper and benefited from his guidance during our first hackathon win, meeting him in person was a moment of profound gratitude.</p>
<p>These interactions underscored the importance of mentorship and personal connections in the world of AI research. They reminded me that behind every algorithm and research paper are human relationships that drive innovation and personal growth.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-and-looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-and-looking-ahead">Reflections and Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>As I reflect on this second day of the Deep Learning Indaba, I’m filled with a sense of optimism and purpose. The convergence of brilliant minds, cutting-edge research, and a shared commitment to ethical AI development creates an environment where true innovation can flourish.</p>
<p>The discussions and presentations today highlighted several key themes that I believe will shape the future of AI in Africa:</p>
<ul>
<li>The importance of developing AI solutions that address uniquely African challenges and opportunities</li>
<li>The critical need for responsible AI practices that consider the diverse ethical and societal implications of these technologies</li>
<li>The power of collaboration and knowledge sharing in accelerating AI innovation across the continent</li>
</ul>
<p>As we move into the latter half of the Indaba, I’m eager to see how these themes will evolve and what new insights will emerge. The energy and intellect gathered here in Dakar are a testament to the bright future of AI in Africa.</p>
<p>Alhamdulillah for another day filled with learning, connection, and inspiration. The Deep Learning Indaba continues to be a catalyst for AI innovation in Africa, and I’m honored to be part of this transformative experience.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates as we continue this exciting journey at the forefront of AI in Africa!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-02/indaba-logo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024: Day 1 Highlights and Reflections</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m thrilled to share my experience from the Deep Learning Indaba 2024, currently happening in Dakar, Senegal, from September 1st to 7th. This event brings together some of the most talented AI minds from across Africa, creating a vibrant and inspiring environment for knowledge exchange, collaboration, and innovation.</p>
<section id="day-1-a-journey-into-probabilistic-programming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-1-a-journey-into-probabilistic-programming">Day 1: A Journey into Probabilistic Programming</h2>
<p>Day 1 kicked off with an exciting mix of registration, introductions, and a variety of sessions that set the tone for the rest of the week. I was honored to lead the practical session on Probabilistic Programming, where I had the chance to tutor participants on essential concepts such as probability, probability distributions, bayes theoerem, and their applications in machine learning.</p>
<p>The session was incredibly rewarding. The participants’ engagement and enthusiasm were evident as we dove deep into understanding how probabilistic thinking forms the backbone of many AI models. It was inspiring to see so many bright minds eager to learn and apply these concepts. If you’d like to explore the notebooks (two parts, both parts in english and french) we used for this session, it’s available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/deep-learning-indaba/indaba-pracs-2024/tree/main/practicals/Probabilistic_Thinking_and_Programming">Probabilistic Thinking and Programming Notebook</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="connecting-with-the-community" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="connecting-with-the-community">Connecting with the Community</h2>
<p>One of the highlights for me was meeting the dynamic duo behind our practical lab—James and Kira. Their hard work and dedication to organizing these sessions were evident, and it was great to share insights and ideas with James from DeepMind and Kira from UCL. We even managed to capture a memorable moment together, which I’ll cherish as a reminder of this wonderful experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="engaging-talks-on-fairness-and-speech-recognition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="engaging-talks-on-fairness-and-speech-recognition">Engaging Talks on Fairness and Speech Recognition</h2>
<p>With so many sessions happening concurrently, choosing which ones to attend was a challenge! I was fortunate enough to participate in two deeply insightful presentations. The first was on fairness in machine learning algorithms, a critical topic that delved into how we can ensure AI systems are fair, ethical, and inclusive. The second presentation focused on automatic speech recognition for low-resource languages, showcasing groundbreaking work that aims to bridge the digital divide and make AI accessible to all communities, regardless of linguistic diversity.</p>
</section>
<section id="celebrating-the-start-of-an-inspiring-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="celebrating-the-start-of-an-inspiring-week">Celebrating the Start of an Inspiring Week</h2>
<p>We capped off the day with a vibrant celebration, marking the official start of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024. The energy was infectious, and it was a fantastic way to unwind and connect with fellow AI enthusiasts from different parts of the continent.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Reflecting on Day 1, I’m filled with gratitude and excitement. It’s truly an honor to be part of such a passionate and forward-thinking community. The discussions, learning, and networking have already been incredible, and I can’t wait to see what the rest of the week has in store.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates, reflections, and possibly pictures from this inspiring event! 📸</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-01/indaba.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Understanding Responsible AI: A Deep Dive into Ethical AI Development</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/responsible-ai/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) is rapidly advancing, transforming industries from healthcare to transportation. With its growing influence, there is an increasing need to ensure that AI is developed and deployed responsibly. This is where Responsible AI (RAI) comes in—a framework designed to guide the ethical use of AI, ensuring fairness, transparency, accountability, and respect for human rights. In this article, I explore the key concepts of Responsible AI, its importance, and how organizations can implement strategies that align AI development with ethical principles.</p>
<p>This article is primarily a summary of the content I learnt in the course <a href="https://app.datacamp.com/learn/courses/responsible-ai-practices">Responsible AI Practices</a> on DataCamp. I enrolled in this course after I had the privilege of reviewing the notebooks for the Responsible AI practicals for the upcoming Deep Learning Indaba 2024 in Dakar, Senegal. This combination of learning and practical experience has given me a well-rounded perspective on the principles of Responsible AI, which I am excited to share. I must also thank Arewa Data Science Academy for giving me the opportunity to enjoy a Data Camp scholarship, which allowed me to learn several concepts and earn relevant certifications for free.</p>
<section id="defining-responsible-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="defining-responsible-ai">Defining Responsible AI</h2>
<p>Responsible AI refers to the practice of designing, developing, and deploying AI systems with an understanding of their ethical implications and societal impacts. It is about ensuring that AI systems are fair, transparent, accountable, and respectful of privacy and human rights. The goal is to create AI that benefits society without causing harm, focusing not only on the technology itself but also on the values guiding its use.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-responsible-ai-is-crucial" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-responsible-ai-is-crucial">Why Responsible AI is Crucial</h2>
<p>AI’s ability to process vast amounts of data and learn from it is revolutionizing fields like healthcare, education, and finance. However, these advancements come with risks. AI can perpetuate biases, invade privacy, or be used unethically if not developed responsibly. For example, facial recognition systems have been found to have higher error rates for people of color, leading to discriminatory outcomes. Similarly, automated hiring systems can reflect and amplify existing biases in the data they are trained on.</p>
<p>These risks highlight the need for Responsible AI practices that mitigate negative impacts and promote fairness and inclusivity. The stakes are high, making Responsible AI a critical aspect of any AI development strategy.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-principles-of-responsible-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-principles-of-responsible-ai">Key Principles of Responsible AI</h2>
<p>The principles of Responsible AI are based on globally recognized guidelines, such as those from the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). Key principles include:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Transparency and Explainability: AI systems should be designed so that their decisions can be understood and explained.</li>
<li>Fairness and Non-Discrimination: AI should be free from biases and discrimination, promoting inclusivity and equity.</li>
<li>Robustness and Safety: AI systems must be reliable, secure, and capable of operating safely in various conditions.</li>
<li>Privacy and Data Governance: AI should respect privacy and ensure secure data handling.</li>
<li>Accountability: Organizations should be accountable for the outcomes of their AI systems.</li>
<li>Inclusive Growth and Sustainability: AI should bridge digital divides and contribute to sustainable development.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="responsible-ai-vs.-ai-ethics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="responsible-ai-vs.-ai-ethics">Responsible AI vs.&nbsp;AI Ethics</h2>
<p>While Responsible AI and AI Ethics are closely related, they are not identical. AI Ethics focuses broadly on the philosophical and moral questions surrounding AI, while Responsible AI is more practical, emphasizing the implementation of ethical considerations in measurable ways. It involves using clear metrics and frameworks to ensure that AI systems align with ethical principles.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-global-regulatory-landscape" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-global-regulatory-landscape">The Global Regulatory Landscape</h2>
<p>Regulation of AI is still evolving, but several regions are leading the way. The European Union’s AI Act classifies AI systems based on risk levels and imposes stringent requirements on high-risk applications. In the United States, initiatives like the AI Bill of Rights and various state-level regulations are shaping AI governance. Countries like Canada, the UK, and China are also developing frameworks tailored to their societal and economic needs.</p>
<p>These regulatory efforts share a common goal: to protect human rights while fostering innovation in AI. As AI technology continues to advance, these regulations will play a critical role in ensuring that AI systems are used responsibly.</p>
</section>
<section id="implementing-responsible-ai-an-8-step-approach" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implementing-responsible-ai-an-8-step-approach">Implementing Responsible AI: An 8-Step Approach</h2>
<p>For organizations looking to implement Responsible AI, the following eight-step approach is recommended:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Embrace AI Governance: Secure organizational commitment to align AI development with ethical standards and business goals.</li>
<li>Build an AI Playbook: Develop a strategic plan that documents AI governance practices, keeping it flexible and up to date.</li>
<li>Identify Key Stakeholders: Engage both internal and external stakeholders to ensure inclusivity and address diverse perspectives.</li>
<li>Leverage Internal Support Mechanisms: Use ethics boards, training programs, and AI squads to guide ethical AI development.</li>
<li>Embrace a Multi-Stakeholder Approach: Include community members, industry experts, and policymakers in AI governance.</li>
<li>Explore Additional Responsible Behavior Indicators: Demonstrate a commitment to Responsible AI through certifications, CSR standards, and transparent ESG reporting.</li>
<li>Implement Governance Tools: Develop guidelines and procedures that uphold Responsible AI principles.</li>
<li>Monitor, Audit, and Evaluate AI Systems: Continuously monitor and audit AI systems to ensure they remain aligned with ethical standards.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="the-importance-of-diversity-in-ai-development" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-importance-of-diversity-in-ai-development">The Importance of Diversity in AI Development</h2>
<p>Diversity, equity, and inclusion (DE&amp;I) are essential for creating fair and unbiased AI systems. A lack of diversity in AI development teams can lead to systems that reflect and reinforce societal biases. For instance, facial recognition systems and hiring algorithms have been shown to produce biased results when developed without diverse perspectives.</p>
<p>Research shows that diverse teams are more innovative and perform better. Prioritizing DE&amp;I in AI development is not just ethically sound but also beneficial for business, leading to more robust and inclusive AI solutions.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-the-path-forward-for-responsible-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-the-path-forward-for-responsible-ai">Conclusion: The Path Forward for Responsible AI</h2>
<p>Responsible AI is a continuous journey that requires ongoing evaluation, monitoring, and adaptation. My recent experience reviewing content for the upcoming Deep Learning Indaba 2024 reinforced the importance of this topic. The principles I learned in the DataCamp course on Responsible AI practices, coupled with my practical experience, have deepened my understanding of the need for ethical AI governance.</p>
<p>As AI continues to evolve, it is our collective responsibility to guide its development in ways that reflect our highest ethical standards. By embracing Responsible AI principles, we can ensure that AI serves humanity in a way that is fair, transparent, and accountable, ultimately contributing to a more equitable and sustainable future.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <category>responsible ai</category>
  <category>datacamp</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/responsible-ai/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/responsible-ai/responsible-ai.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="83" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
