<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>ailearningloop</title>
<link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/</link>
<atom:link href="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Venturing Beyond My Roots: An AI Odyssey Unfolds for This Non-Tech Trailblazer!</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>On Being Featured by DeepLearning.AI: A Milestone in My AI Journey</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dlai-feature/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A significant milestone in my artificial intelligence journey recently materialized when DeepLearning.AI featured my story across their global platforms. The recognition came from a forum post where I shared my experiences as a course tester and mentor, reflecting on a journey that began in January 2023 with Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning Specialization.</p>
<section id="the-journey-to-recognition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-journey-to-recognition">The Journey to Recognition</h2>
<p>My involvement with DeepLearning.AI has been transformative. What started as enrolling in a single course evolved into a deep engagement with the AI community. As a course tester, I’ve had the privilege of providing feedback that helps shape the learning experience for future students. In my role as a mentor, I’ve guided numerous learners through the complexities of machine learning, witnessing their growth from novices to confident practitioners.</p>
</section>
<section id="global-reach-and-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="global-reach-and-impact">Global Reach and Impact</h2>
<p>The feature was shared across DeepLearning.AI’s extensive social media network:</p>
<ul>
<li>LinkedIn showcased my journey to their professional network of AI enthusiasts</li>
<li>X (formerly Twitter) broadcast my story to the global tech community</li>
<li>Facebook reached aspiring AI practitioners worldwide</li>
<li>Instagram captured the visual narrative of my path in AI</li>
</ul>
<p>A particularly touching moment came when my friend Abbas shared the Instagram feature with me—a reminder of how supportive the tech community can be.</p>
</section>
<section id="professional-growth-and-future-aspirations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="professional-growth-and-future-aspirations">Professional Growth and Future Aspirations</h2>
<p>This recognition arrives at a pivotal moment in my career. After three enriching years at Zipline, where I applied AI to revolutionize medical delivery systems in Africa, I’m preparing for new challenges. My experience has reinforced my belief in AI’s potential to transform healthcare delivery in developing regions. The intersection of my pharmaceutical background with artificial intelligence has positioned me uniquely in the healthcare-tech space. At Zipline, I’ve witnessed firsthand how AI can optimize medical supply chains and improve access to healthcare in remote areas.</p>
</section>
<section id="community-impact-and-mentorship" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-impact-and-mentorship">Community Impact and Mentorship</h2>
<p>One of my proudest achievements has been mentoring in the AI community. Through DeepLearning.AI’s platform, I’ve had the opportunity to: - Guide aspiring data scientists through complex concepts - Share practical insights from real-world AI applications - Build a supportive network of learners and practitioners - Contribute to making AI education more accessible</p>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>This recognition from DeepLearning.AI has reinforced my commitment to advancing AI education and application in healthcare. As I prepare for the next chapter in my career, I remain dedicated to: - Continuing to mentor and support aspiring AI practitioners - Contributing to the development of AI solutions in healthcare - Building bridges between technology and healthcare delivery - Advancing AI education in Africa</p>
</section>
<section id="social-media-links" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="social-media-links">Social Media Links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://x.com/DeepLearningAI/status/1853618233384878573">View on X (Twitter)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/deeplearningai_an-inspiring-journey-from-nigeria-see-how-activity-7259383961997475840-BGqC">Read on LinkedIn</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/1CsDcrJucT/">Facebook Post</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.instagram.com/deeplearningai/p/DB-N2SPM9fO/">Instagram Feature</a></li>
</ul>
<p>In sha Allah, this milestone marks just the beginning of greater achievements to come. I’m deeply grateful for the support of my community, mentors, and colleagues who have been part of this journey. As we continue to push the boundaries of what’s possible with AI, I look forward to contributing to more innovations that make a real difference in people’s lives.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <category>career-milestone</category>
  <category>ai-education</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dlai-feature/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Completing the Analyzing Genomic Data in R track on DataCamp</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/genomic-data-analysis/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I just completed DataCamp’s “Analyzing Genomic Data in R” track, which was an incredible dive into using R and Bioconductor for genomic analysis. This track had four in-depth courses that helped me build skills for analyzing genomic datasets:</p>
<ul>
<li>Introduction to Bioconductor in R</li>
<li>RNA-Seq with Bioconductor in R</li>
<li>Differential Expression Analysis with limma in R</li>
<li>ChIP-seq with Bioconductor in R</li>
</ul>
<p>In this post, I’ll briefly walk you through each course and share what I learned and why it was so exciting.</p>
<section id="introduction-to-bioconductor-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-to-bioconductor-in-r">Introduction to Bioconductor in R</h2>
<p>This course was my gateway to Bioconductor—an essential resource for genomic analysis in R. I learned how to install packages with the BiocInstaller, work with different types of genomic data, and explore real-life datasets like those for fungi, viruses, and even plants. Tools like BioStrings, GenomicRanges, and ShortRead made manipulating and filtering raw data surprisingly accessible.</p>
<p>One highlight was learning to use built-in datasets (BSgenome and TxDb) and apply functions to search for patterns in genomic sequences. Quality control was another important aspect, using ShortRead and Rqc to ensure that my data was clean and usable—a crucial step in genomic research.</p>
</section>
<section id="rna-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rna-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r">RNA-Seq with Bioconductor in R</h2>
<p>In this course, I got hands-on with RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) data, focusing on differential expression analysis—identifying genes that express differently between experimental conditions. I used DESeq2 to analyze gene expression between fibrosis and normal samples, which was a powerful introduction to understanding biological significance in genomics.</p>
<p>An interesting takeaway was the reminder that data interpretation doesn’t stop at identifying significant genes. I learned that experimental validation is key—around 5% of “significant” results are false positives, and ensuring that our findings are accurate requires lab-based verification. Additionally, I explored how functional analysis can help us see the biological meaning behind the data by identifying enriched processes or pathways.</p>
</section>
<section id="differential-expression-analysis-with-limma-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="differential-expression-analysis-with-limma-in-r">Differential Expression Analysis with limma in R</h2>
<p>This course added another layer to my understanding of differential expression—specifically using limma, a versatile and widely-used Bioconductor package. I visualized gene expression levels with plotDensities and normalized raw data to ensure reliable analysis. One key aspect was principal component analysis (plotMDS), which helped me see whether data variation matched my experimental variables or if there were other technical factors at play.</p>
<p>I also learned to identify important genes using volcano plots and assess results using p-value distributions. The course highlighted how essential quality control is, emphasizing the need for careful examination to avoid misleading conclusions. Wrapping up, I conducted gene set enrichment analysis to explore biological pathways using KEGG and Gene Ontology databases—this really helped broaden my perspective from individual genes to broader biological systems.</p>
</section>
<section id="chip-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chip-seq-with-bioconductor-in-r">ChIP-seq with Bioconductor in R</h2>
<p>ChIP-seq (Chromatin Immunoprecipitation Sequencing) was the final frontier in this track, and it was challenging but incredibly rewarding. I learned to import ChIP-seq data using rtracklayer and GenomicAlignments, visualize it with Gviz, and ensure its quality by dealing with repetitive regions through blacklisting and QC reports with ChIPQC.</p>
<p>The analysis culminated in using DiffBind to identify differentially bound peaks and create heatmaps and PCA plots to understand sample clustering. Finally, I used the chipenrich package to link peaks to nearby genes and performed enrichment analysis to see which biological processes were associated with these binding events. This part of the course really helped tie everything together and made me confident about analyzing real-world ChIP-seq data.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-on-the-journey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-the-journey">Reflections on the Journey</h2>
<p>Completing this track gave me practical skills to handle various genomic datasets and analyze them meaningfully. Each course built on the previous one, reinforcing core concepts while adding new techniques, ultimately providing a well-rounded introduction to genomic analysis in R.</p>
<p>My next step is to apply what I’ve learned to real datasets—perhaps even contribute to open research initiatives. Bioconductor’s community and support forums will be great allies as I dive deeper into genomics. As I am seriously considering grad school, this is a skill that will help me immensely in the pursuit of my goals.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/genomic-data-analysis/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/genomic-data-analysis/genomic-analysis.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="83" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Completing the Health Informatics Specialization on Coursera</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/health-informatics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am excited to announce that I have completed the Health Informatics Specialization offered by Johns Hopkins University on Coursera. This learning journey, which began in November while I was in Rwanda, has taken me across different geographies—from Kaduna to Ogoja in Cross River State, and even to Senegal—and has finally concluded in Nigeria.</p>
<p>The specialization was a deep dive into the world of Health Informatics, offering a comprehensive understanding of both the social and technical dimensions of the field. It comprised five meticulously curated courses, each providing unique insights and knowledge essential for anyone interested in the intersection of healthcare and information technology.</p>
<p>The Social and Technical Context of Health Informatics: This course laid the foundation, exploring the broader contexts in which health informatics operates. It helped me appreciate the complexities involved in integrating technology into healthcare systems, especially in low-resource settings.</p>
<p>Leading Change in Health Informatics: This was my favorite course, expertly taught by Dr.&nbsp;Ashwini Davison. It resonated deeply with me as it discussed the challenges and strategies for implementing change in healthcare systems—a critical issue for countries like Nigeria, where the adoption of electronic health records (EHRs) is still in its infancy. The course provided practical frameworks and tools for driving change, which I found incredibly valuable.</p>
<p>The Outcomes and Interventions of Health Informatics: This course offered a deep understanding of the types of interventions that can be made using health informatics and how to measure their outcomes. It provided insights into how data can be leveraged to drive decision-making and improve patient care.</p>
<p>The Data Science of Health Informatics: As someone who has been delving into data science for a while, this course was a perfect blend of my interests. It covered critical data science concepts and techniques relevant to health informatics, enhancing my ability to analyze and interpret complex health data.</p>
<p>Culminating Project in Health Informatics: The final course brought everything together with a project-based approach. We were tasked with analyzing a real-world scenario involving ImprovingHealth, a non-profit healthcare organization facing challenges in implementing systematic Health-Related Social Needs (HRSN) screenings across its clinics. The project highlighted the inefficiencies in paper-based data collection methods and the lack of adequate staff training and buy-in, which were significant barriers to identifying and addressing social determinants of health for Medicare beneficiaries.</p>
<p>Reflecting on this journey, I realize how far-reaching the impact of health informatics can be, particularly in enhancing healthcare delivery and improving patient outcomes. The specialization has equipped me with the knowledge and skills to better understand and tackle the challenges in this field, especially in regions where healthcare systems face significant technological and infrastructural barriers.</p>
<p>I look forward to applying these insights and continuing to contribute to the evolution of digital health and health informatics in meaningful ways. I am especially excited about the potential for collaboration and innovation that lies ahead.</p>
<p>Thank you to all the instructors and fellow learners who made this journey enriching and rewarding!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates on my journey into health informatics and how we can leverage data for better health outcomes. 🚀</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>informatics</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/health-informatics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/health-informatics/health-informatics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="92" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024 Day 6: A Journey Through Inspiring Workshops and Innovation in Health AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-06/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s hard to believe that we’re already at Day 6 of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024! Time seems to have flown by, and it’s incredible to think that there’s only one more day left. The Indaba has been a whirlwind of knowledge, networking, and inspiration. Today was a day dedicated to workshops, and the challenge was real: so many fascinating topics were on the table, but they all ran simultaneously!</p>
<p>The workshops available today were diverse and compelling, each catering to different facets of AI and machine learning in Africa. Here’s a glimpse of the workshops I had to choose from:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Weakly Supervised Computer Vision Workshop: Exploring techniques that allow models to learn from limited labeled data, a crucial need in regions where data labeling is resource-intensive.</p></li>
<li><p>The NeuroAI Workshop: Bridging neuroscience and AI, focusing on how principles from the brain can be applied to AI systems, and vice versa.</p></li>
<li><p>Empowering African Voices in AI: A discussion on inclusivity and the importance of representation in AI, promoting diversity of thought and experience.</p></li>
<li><p>Voices of Africa: Building the Infrastructure for African NLP: This workshop focused on developing natural language processing (NLP) tools and datasets that reflect the diversity of African languages, essential for creating inclusive AI applications.</p></li>
<li><p>AfriClimateAI - Uniting for Climate-Resilient Africa: Bringing together experts and practitioners to discuss the role of AI in tackling climate change in Africa, fostering data and knowledge exchange to build a more climate-resilient future.</p></li>
<li><p>Robot Learning for Africa Workshop: Delving into how robotics and machine learning can be leveraged for various applications in the African context, from agriculture to healthcare.</p></li>
<li><p>Data Science for Health in Africa Workshop: Organized by Sisonke Biotik and Ro’ya, two grassroots communities focused on Machine Learning and Global Health in Africa, this workshop looked at innovative approaches to using data science in healthcare.</p></li>
<li><p>AI for Good Symposium in Africa: Highlighting projects and research that use AI to address pressing social issues and contribute to sustainable development across the continent.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>With so many great choices, it was difficult to decide, but ultimately, my interest in the intersection of AI and health led me to attend the Data Science for Health in Africa workshop.</p>
<section id="diving-deep-into-ai-for-health-in-africa" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diving-deep-into-ai-for-health-in-africa">Diving Deep into AI for Health in Africa</h2>
<p>The workshop, jointly organized by Sisonke Biotik and Ro’ya, was a hub of activity and collaboration. Both organizations are grassroots, participatory communities focused on advancing Machine Learning and Global Health in Africa. The sessions were highly interactive, and the atmosphere was one of shared learning and innovation.</p>
<p>We started with a practical workshop on using R for health data algorithms, which was particularly valuable for practitioners and researchers interested in leveraging open-source tools for health analytics. It was a hands-on session that allowed participants to get acquainted with different techniques and tools for analyzing complex health datasets.</p>
</section>
<section id="insights-from-ai-pioneers-in-health" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insights-from-ai-pioneers-in-health">Insights from AI Pioneers in Health</h2>
<p>The workshop featured a range of insightful presentations. Among the highlights were:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Muhammad Al-Fatih’s Presentation on SKAI: SKAI (Satellite Knowledge Augmented Intelligence) is an innovative platform that utilizes AI and satellite imagery to provide real-time insights and actionable intelligence. This is particularly crucial for effective decision-making during disaster response, where timely information can save lives. Muhammad walked us through how SKAI integrates different data sources and uses AI to analyze satellite imagery, making it a game-changer for disaster management and emergency response in Africa.</p></li>
<li><p>Mercy Asiedu’s Talk on Multifaceted Approaches to AI for Health in Africa: Mercy’s presentation was a deep dive into the multiple ways AI can be leveraged for health in Africa. She touched on the importance of benchmark datasets for health on the continent, noting that these datasets must reflect the diverse population to be truly impactful. The talk also covered innovative AI solutions that address specific health challenges in Africa, emphasizing the need for culturally and contextually relevant technologies.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="collaborative-innovation-pitching-ideas-to-revolutionize-healthcare" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="collaborative-innovation-pitching-ideas-to-revolutionize-healthcare">Collaborative Innovation: Pitching Ideas to Revolutionize Healthcare</h2>
<p>One of the most exciting parts of the day was a collaborative session where participants were grouped together to pitch an idea that could potentially revolutionize healthcare in Africa. This was a fantastic opportunity to brainstorm and exchange ideas with people from diverse backgrounds, ranging from data scientists to healthcare professionals. The energy in the room was palpable, and the ideas that came out of these discussions were both creative and practical.</p>
</section>
<section id="speed-presentations-and-ideathon-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speed-presentations-and-ideathon-results">Speed Presentations and Ideathon Results</h2>
<p>To add to the excitement, there was a speed presentation competition where participants had a few minutes to present their innovative ideas or research findings. This fast-paced format was engaging and showcased the breadth of talent and creativity present at the Indaba.</p>
<p>Additionally, the results of the Ideathon, which was held a day earlier, were announced today. My team, NextGen Health Innovators, was thrilled to be awarded third place! We were recognized for our innovative solution aimed at improving vaccine delivery through AI and data science. Receiving our certificate and prize was a moment of pride and joy, capping off what has been an incredible day of learning and collaboration.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-and-looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-and-looking-ahead">Reflections and Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>Reflecting on today, I can confidently say it has been my best day at the Indaba so far. The workshops were about learning and connecting with like-minded individuals, exchanging ideas, and envisioning a future where AI can truly make a difference in healthcare across Africa. It was a day filled with inspiration, and it reinforced my belief in the power of collaboration and innovation.</p>
<p>It’s a bit bittersweet to realize that the Indaba is almost over. Tomorrow marks the final day, and while I’m looking forward to what it has in store, I can’t help but feel a little nostalgic already. The Deep Learning Indaba has been more than just a conference; it’s been a journey of growth, learning, and connection.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-06/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-06/lukman-dakar.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflecting on the Final Day of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024: A Journey of Insights and Inspiration</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-07/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As the saying goes, every beginning has an end, and the final day of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024 marked the conclusion of a week filled with knowledge-sharing, networking, and inspiration. This year’s Indaba was a true testament to the diversity and depth of AI conversations shaping Africa’s future. The final day was no exception, featuring several concurrent half-day workshops that challenged us to choose just one path to follow!</p>
<p>The workshop options were diverse, each promising to delve into a unique aspect of AI and its potential impact:</p>
<ul>
<li>Envisioning Humans in a Safe, AI Future</li>
<li>GeoAI for a Sustainable Future in Africa</li>
<li>Empowering Africa’s AI Future through High Performance and Cloud Computing</li>
<li>AI Regulation in Africa: Rationale, Considerations, and Way Forward</li>
</ul>
<p>I opted for the “Envisioning Humans in a Safe, AI Future” workshop, a choice that proved to be the right one for me. However, I must admit it was a tough call—each workshop offered something valuable, and it was unfortunate that I couldn’t attend them all. Alas, one can only be in one place at a time!</p>
<p>The workshop began with an introduction to ML Commons, an open initiative that aims to accelerate machine learning research, and ways to get involved. This set the stage for the discussions that followed, starting with a panel discussion on “Seeking Safer Spaces with AI Tools.” The panelists brought forward intriguing perspectives on how we can create AI tools that foster safer and more inclusive environments. The discussions were not only thought-provoking but also a call to action for all of us in the AI community.</p>
<p>Following the panel, we moved on to a segment titled “Behind the Research: Author Insights.” This session provided a deeper look into the journeys and motivations of researchers working at the intersection of AI and social good. It was inspiring to hear firsthand about the challenges they faced, the breakthroughs they achieved, and the lessons they learned along the way.</p>
<p>The workshop wrapped up with some final announcements and reflections on the discussions held throughout the day. As a token of appreciation for our engagement in this packed and event-studded session, all participants received certificates of attendance—a wonderful keepsake to remember this enriching experience.</p>
<p>After the workshops, the Wangari Maathai Impact Award was presented to Grace Muthoni for her groundbreaking research. Her work stood out among many, and it was heartening to see such talent being recognized and celebrated. Congratulations to Grace!</p>
<p>The day then transitioned into the final Indaba panel discussion, which served as a comprehensive summary of the entire event. The panel, composed of notable experts and thought leaders, tackled critical themes such as the need for skilling, foundational research, and the concept of human-in-the-loop AI—all while emphasizing the importance of not losing our unique identities as we navigate the evolving AI landscape.</p>
<p>One of the most compelling parts of the discussion was the exploration of future research directions, including the relationship between language and machine learning education, and AI’s potential role in tackling climate change. It was an important reminder that while it’s easy to get caught up in trending topics, our research should be driven by genuine curiosity and the unique challenges we wish to solve.</p>
<p>A major takeaway from the panel was the affirmation that our experiences are uniquely ours and that they are a valuable asset in shaping our paths in AI. No one else can walk our path for us, and leveraging our unique backgrounds and perspectives can lead to innovative and impactful contributions to the field.</p>
<p>Throughout the week, I’ve been sharing my experiences from Indaba, as encouraged, and it has been truly inspiring to see the passion and commitment of AI practitioners across the continent.</p>
<p>The final day concluded with a vibrant closing ceremony, where prizes were awarded to deserving winners, followed by a celebratory closing party that was filled with joy, music, and a sense of accomplishment. With that, Deep Learning Indaba 2024 came to a close.</p>
<p>But this isn’t goodbye—it’s simply “see you next year.” The next Indaba will be held in Kigali, Rwanda, and I’m already looking forward to the incredible conversations and experiences that await us there.</p>
<p>Stay tuned, and see you in Kigali next year!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-07/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024:Day 5, A Day of Insights, Innovation, and Inspiration</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Day 5 of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024 was filled with moments that highlighted the vibrancy and depth of AI research and innovation happening across Africa. The day began with a celebration of academic excellence as Fiskani Banda received the Grace Alele-Williams Masters Award for her outstanding master’s thesis. Her dedication to pushing the boundaries of knowledge is a true inspiration for all of us in the AI community.</p>
<p>Following this uplifting moment, we moved into a thought-provoking keynote by Dr.&nbsp;Judy Gichoya, Associate Professor of Radiology and Informatics at Emory University. Dr.&nbsp;Gichoya’s presentation, “Shortcuts Causing Bias in Medical Imaging,” was a deep dive into the often-overlooked issue of shortcut learning in AI. She skillfully unpacked how biases can stem from both dataset limitations and the nature of discriminative learning itself. This session resonated with me profoundly, particularly given my interest in the intersection of AI and health. It served as a powerful reminder of the need for transparency and understanding in AI models, especially when they are applied to critical fields like healthcare where biases can have real-world consequences.</p>
<p>The day’s agenda then shifted to a series of research showcases, demonstrating the diverse and impactful AI work being done across the continent. From using pre-trained models for essay scoring to flood prediction models and innovative approaches to predicting and preventing farmer-herder conflicts, the research presentations covered a wide array of domains. Each project underscored the potential of AI to address both local and global challenges, reaffirming the importance of inclusive and context-aware AI development.</p>
<p>I also had the opportunity to attend the Data Science for Health Ideathon. This was a dynamic and engaging session that brought together bright minds to brainstorm and propose innovative AI solutions for health challenges in Africa. The creativity and passion in the room were palpable, making it one of the most energizing parts of the day.</p>
<p>The afternoon featured a panel discussion and presentations from African startups, many of which are harnessing AI to tackle pressing issues on the continent. It’s always inspiring to see how these emerging companies are pushing the envelope and driving impact through AI.</p>
<p>Another significant session was the Faculty Engagement discussion, a first at Indaba. Faculty members from universities across Africa and beyond came together to share insights, challenges, and solutions for advancing AI education and research on the continent. It was a meaningful conversation, and I’m excited to hear that this will be a recurring feature at future Indabas.</p>
<p>Between sessions, I made sure to network with other attendees, exchanging ideas and learning about their work. I also visited the booths of various Indaba partners, gaining a deeper understanding of the incredible projects and initiatives they are supporting.</p>
<p>As the day concluded, I found myself reflecting on how each day at the Indaba seems to surpass the last. The experiences, the learning, and the connections all continue to make this journey incredibly rewarding. I can’t wait to see what the next days have in store!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates from Deep Learning Indaba 2024!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024:Day 4, Celebrating African Research, Learning, and Community Building</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-04/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today at Deep Learning Indaba 2024 was nothing short of inspiring! As the event unfolds, I’m continually amazed by the depth and diversity of research being conducted across Africa. Here’s a recap of my fourth day:</p>
<p><strong>Celebrating African Research Excellence</strong>: The day began with the Indaba Kambule Doctoral Thesis Award ceremony, which recognizes outstanding doctoral research by African scholars. This award is a testament to the originality and impact of research emerging from the continent, highlighting the innovative spirit driving Africa forward in AI and data science.</p>
<p><strong>Diving into Oral Presentations and Poster Sessions</strong>: The day continued with IndabaX Oral Presentations and two sessions of Poster Presentations. The posters showcased a range of exciting research:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deep Learning-Based Lesion Segmentation for Early Liver Tumor Detection in Rwanda: Using a hybrid ResNet-UNet model, researchers presented significant results in early tumor detection from liver CT scans—a major step forward for healthcare in Rwanda.</li>
<li>siSwatiSent: Sentiment Analysis Dataset for siSwati: A unique sentiment analysis dataset for the siSwati language, extracted from YouTube comments. This study emphasizes the need for more African language resources in NLP.</li>
<li>CHOWNET-V1: An Image Dataset of Nigerian Food: A fascinating dataset that addresses the underrepresentation of African cuisine in machine learning research, enhancing diversity in food classification tasks.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Mentorship and Knowledge Sharing</strong>: I was fortunate to join a mentorship session with Georgina Curto Rex. Our discussion revolved around the importance of selecting meaningful problems to work on and the role of having a guiding purpose as we explore various research avenues. This session was a reminder that our work should always aim to make a real-world impact.</p>
<p><strong>Understanding the Limitations of LLMs</strong>: The keynote lecture by Caglar Gulcehre focused on the limitations of large language models (LLMs). It was an eye-opening discussion that explored both the capabilities and the constraints of these models, sparking ideas on how we might improve and innovate further in the field.</p>
<p><strong>Learning to Publish</strong>: The day wrapped up with a Research Writing event, where we were taught the nuances of writing and publishing impactful research papers. This session was invaluable for anyone looking to contribute meaningfully to the academic community.</p>
<p><strong>A Memorable Arewa Data Science Connect</strong>: The day ended on a high note with our Arewa Data Science connect session. It was heartwarming to take a picture with my fellow Arewa Data Science folks at Indaba—strengthening our sense of community and shared purpose in advancing data science across Africa.</p>
<p><strong>A New Discovery</strong>: On a lighter note, I discovered a new country today—Eswatini! It was a humbling moment, reminding me of the endless learning opportunities that events like this bring.</p>
<p><strong>Reflecting on the Day</strong>: Today was a blend of knowledge, mentorship, and community. I feel incredibly fortunate to be part of this transformative event that is shaping the future of AI and data science in Africa. Here’s to more learning, connecting, and growing together!</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates from Deep Learning Indaba 2024!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-04/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-04/arewadsdli.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024:Day 3, A Day of Insights, Innovation, and Inspiration</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Attending the Deep Learning Indaba 2024 in Dakar has been a whirlwind of learning, networking, and inspiration. Day 3 was particularly packed with enriching activities and thought-provoking sessions that left me energized and inspired.</p>
<p>The day began with a compelling keynote by Samy Bengio on “Learning to Reason.” Samy delved deep into the challenges that transformer models still face when it comes to reasoning. While transformers have revolutionized natural language processing, their ability to reason like humans remains limited. Samy presented some innovative methods to enhance this reasoning ability, sparking a lively discussion among attendees. It was fascinating to see how research continues to push the boundaries of what AI can achieve.</p>
<p>After the keynote, I attended a hands-on practical session on Federated Learning. Having spent the last two days tutoring, it was refreshing to be on the learning side again. We explored how federated learning can play a crucial role in fostering responsible AI, particularly by ensuring data privacy and security. We also got hands-on with Flower, an open-source framework for building federated learning systems, and discussed the added complexities that arise when working with heterogeneous datasets. Thanks to my prior experience with the DeepLearning.AI Federated Learning short course, I could dive deeper into the challenges and opportunities in this space.</p>
<p>Next, I joined a career mentorship session with Sekou Remy from IBM. This was one of the highlights of my day, as Sekou shared invaluable advice on navigating one’s career in AI. Some key takeaways included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Make decisions based on the evidence you can gather while planning your future.</li>
<li>Take advantage of internships during undergrad and grad school; they are invaluable for gaining experience.</li>
<li>Find a balance between acquiring new knowledge (exploration) and applying what you know (exploitation).</li>
<li>Time is your most valuable asset—use it wisely.</li>
<li>AI offers significant potential in data capture and analysis.</li>
<li>Always keep an open mind and be willing to learn.</li>
<li>Networking is not just a buzzword; it is key to professional growth.</li>
</ul>
<p>This session was a reminder of the importance of being strategic, adaptable, and proactive in our career journeys.</p>
<p>After that, I attended a fascinating session on “Multimodal Perception for Human and Animal Behavior Understanding,” led by Marwa Mahmoud from the University of Glasgow’s Behavioural AI Laboratory. Marwa discussed her work on the early detection of neurodevelopmental conditions in children using multimodal features, highlighting the critical need for explainable and interpretable models. Given that these models are designed to assist healthcare providers, transparency in AI decisions is paramount. She also touched on the use of probabilistic models as a first line of support in decision-making.</p>
<p>What struck me was the complexity and subjectivity involved in applying AI to psychology and behavior analysis, where getting well-labeled datasets can be incredibly challenging. Marwa also provided a glimpse into her work on modeling animal behavior, which can be even more daunting than human behavior. She referenced her paper, “Going Deeper than Tracking: A Survey of Computer Vision-Based Recognition of Animal Pain and Affective States,” which further explores these complexities.</p>
<p>To wrap up the day, I joined discussions on community programs, featuring inspiring talks from various AI communities like GhanaAI, Masakhane, and others. They shared their initiatives and the tangible impacts they’ve made in their regions. It was a powerful reminder of the importance of community in driving AI forward, especially in underrepresented regions. The discussions were filled with passion and a shared vision of using AI for good.</p>
<p>Throughout the day, I also had the opportunity to network with fellow attendees, exchange ideas, and work on our hackathon submission. The energy and camaraderie in the room were palpable, and it was exciting to be part of a community so dedicated to pushing the boundaries of AI.</p>
<p>Day 3 at Deep Learning Indaba 2024 was truly a day of insights, innovation, and inspiration—a perfect blend of learning, sharing, and growing together. I am looking forward to what the rest of the week will bring!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Day 2 at Deep Learning Indaba 2024: Bridging AI Innovation and Ethics in Africa</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-02/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As the sun rose over Dakar, Senegal, it marked the beginning of another exhilarating day at the Deep Learning Indaba 2024. Hosted by the prestigious Université Amadou Mahtar Mbow, this gathering of brilliant minds from across Africa continues to push the boundaries of AI innovation on the continent. Today’s experiences were nothing short of transformative, blending cutting-edge technology with ethical considerations and a spirit of collaboration that defines the African AI community.</p>
<section id="morning-keynote-causethical-ml---from-theory-to-practice" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="morning-keynote-causethical-ml---from-theory-to-practice">Morning Keynote: Causethical ML - From Theory to Practice</h2>
<p>The day kicked off with an enlightening keynote on Causethical Machine Learning. This session delved into the critical intersection of causal inference and ethical AI, emphasizing a fundamental principle: algorithms should not only be efficient but also fair and grounded in ethically acceptable reasoning.</p>
<p>The speaker articulated a compelling vision where fairness in AI isn’t just a moral imperative but a practical one. By ensuring that our algorithms make decisions based on ethically sound principles, we create a win-win scenario. Not only do we uphold justice and equality, but we also create systems that benefit all stakeholders in the long run. This approach to AI development resonates deeply with the African context, where technology must be developed with a keen awareness of diverse societal needs and historical inequities.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-for-good-microsofts-vision-for-positive-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-for-good-microsofts-vision-for-positive-impact">AI for Good: Microsoft’s Vision for Positive Impact</h2>
<p>Following the keynote, we had the privilege of hearing from representatives of the Microsoft AI for Good Research Lab. Their presentation was a testament to the transformative power of AI when applied to pressing global challenges.</p>
</section>
<section id="pushing-boundaries-snake-venom-analysis-using-large-language-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pushing-boundaries-snake-venom-analysis-using-large-language-models">Pushing Boundaries: Snake Venom Analysis Using Large Language Models</h2>
<p>One of the most fascinating sessions of the day focused on an unexpected application of AI: analyzing and sequencing snake venom using Large Language Models (LLMs). This presentation was a perfect example of how AI can revolutionize even the most specialized scientific fields. The researchers demonstrated how they’ve adapted LLMs, typically used for processing human languages, to “read” the complex molecular structures of various snake venoms. This application has enormous potential for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Accelerating the development of antivenoms</li>
<li>Identifying new compounds for pharmaceutical research</li>
<li>Enhancing our understanding of snake biology and evolution</li>
</ul>
<p>As someone deeply interested in both AI and biodiversity, I found this session to be a brilliant demonstration of interdisciplinary research. It showcased how AI tools developed for one domain can find groundbreaking applications in entirely different fields.</p>
</section>
<section id="hands-on-learning-tutoring-responsible-ai-practicals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hands-on-learning-tutoring-responsible-ai-practicals">Hands-on Learning: Tutoring Responsible AI Practicals</h2>
<p>A personal highlight of my day was the opportunity to serve as a tutor for the Responsible AI practicals. Having reviewed the notebooks ahead of the Indaba, I was excited to guide participants through the intricacies of developing AI systems with ethical considerations at their core. The notebooks (English and French) are available on <a href="https://github.com/deep-learning-indaba/indaba-pracs-2024/tree/main/practicals/Responsible_AI">github</a></p>
<p>What struck me most was the eagerness of the participants to engage with these critical issues. Their questions and insights reflected a deep understanding of the potential impacts of AI on African societies and a commitment to developing technologies that uplift rather than marginalize.</p>
<p>These sessions embodied the Indaba’s theme of “Xam Xamlé” – to gain knowledge and share it. The collaborative spirit in the room was palpable, with participants from various countries sharing their unique perspectives on responsible AI development.</p>
</section>
<section id="inspiring-vision-building-up-the-future-of-ai-in-africa" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="inspiring-vision-building-up-the-future-of-ai-in-africa">Inspiring Vision: Building Up the Future of AI in Africa</h2>
<p>The day concluded with an electrifying presentation by Karim Beguir titled “Building Up the Future of AI in Africa.” Beguir’s talk was a rallying cry for African AI researchers and developers, emphasizing that we are living in an unprecedented era of opportunity.</p>
<p>Key points from his presentation included:</p>
<ul>
<li>The democratization of AI tools, with resources like Llama 3.1 now accessible to researchers across the continent</li>
<li>The groundbreaking work being done at InstaDeep, showcasing African-led innovation in AI</li>
<li>An overview of Project Tatooine, a collaboration with GoMyCode aimed at nurturing the next generation of AI talent in Africa, particularly in less developed locations.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Beguir’s central message</strong> – that “agents are the future” – sparked intense discussions among attendees. The vision of AI agents autonomously solving complex problems, tailored to African contexts, opened up exciting possibilities for innovation across various sectors.</p>
</section>
<section id="networking-and-collaboration-the-heart-of-indaba" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="networking-and-collaboration-the-heart-of-indaba">Networking and Collaboration: The Heart of Indaba</h2>
<p>While the formal sessions were incredibly informative, some of the most valuable moments came from the connections made between sessions. The Indaba’s atmosphere encourages spontaneous discussions and collaborations, leading to some exciting developments:</p>
<p>I joined two hackathons – one hosted by Meta and another by InstaDeep. These events are not just competitions but incubators for ideas that could evolve into impactful projects.</p>
<p>The coffee breaks buzzed with energy as participants exchanged ideas, formed impromptu working groups, and planned future collaborations.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-moment-of-personal-connection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-moment-of-personal-connection">A Moment of Personal Connection</h2>
<p>Amidst the whirlwind of activities, I experienced a deeply meaningful personal moment. After nearly two years of virtual collaboration, I finally met Dr.&nbsp;Shamsuddeen Hassan Muhammad in person. Our work together has been a source of immense learning and growth for me, and meeting face-to-face was an emotional and inspiring experience.</p>
<p>I also had the pleasure of meeting Dr.&nbsp;Idris Abdulmumin, another mentor who has played a crucial role in my journey. Having collaborated on a paper and benefited from his guidance during our first hackathon win, meeting him in person was a moment of profound gratitude.</p>
<p>These interactions underscored the importance of mentorship and personal connections in the world of AI research. They reminded me that behind every algorithm and research paper are human relationships that drive innovation and personal growth.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-and-looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-and-looking-ahead">Reflections and Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>As I reflect on this second day of the Deep Learning Indaba, I’m filled with a sense of optimism and purpose. The convergence of brilliant minds, cutting-edge research, and a shared commitment to ethical AI development creates an environment where true innovation can flourish.</p>
<p>The discussions and presentations today highlighted several key themes that I believe will shape the future of AI in Africa:</p>
<ul>
<li>The importance of developing AI solutions that address uniquely African challenges and opportunities</li>
<li>The critical need for responsible AI practices that consider the diverse ethical and societal implications of these technologies</li>
<li>The power of collaboration and knowledge sharing in accelerating AI innovation across the continent</li>
</ul>
<p>As we move into the latter half of the Indaba, I’m eager to see how these themes will evolve and what new insights will emerge. The energy and intellect gathered here in Dakar are a testament to the bright future of AI in Africa.</p>
<p>Alhamdulillah for another day filled with learning, connection, and inspiration. The Deep Learning Indaba continues to be a catalyst for AI innovation in Africa, and I’m honored to be part of this transformative experience.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates as we continue this exciting journey at the forefront of AI in Africa!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-02/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-02/indaba-logo.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deep Learning Indaba 2024: Day 1 Highlights and Reflections</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-01/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m thrilled to share my experience from the Deep Learning Indaba 2024, currently happening in Dakar, Senegal, from September 1st to 7th. This event brings together some of the most talented AI minds from across Africa, creating a vibrant and inspiring environment for knowledge exchange, collaboration, and innovation.</p>
<section id="day-1-a-journey-into-probabilistic-programming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-1-a-journey-into-probabilistic-programming">Day 1: A Journey into Probabilistic Programming</h2>
<p>Day 1 kicked off with an exciting mix of registration, introductions, and a variety of sessions that set the tone for the rest of the week. I was honored to lead the practical session on Probabilistic Programming, where I had the chance to tutor participants on essential concepts such as probability, probability distributions, bayes theoerem, and their applications in machine learning.</p>
<p>The session was incredibly rewarding. The participants’ engagement and enthusiasm were evident as we dove deep into understanding how probabilistic thinking forms the backbone of many AI models. It was inspiring to see so many bright minds eager to learn and apply these concepts. If you’d like to explore the notebooks (two parts, both parts in english and french) we used for this session, it’s available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/deep-learning-indaba/indaba-pracs-2024/tree/main/practicals/Probabilistic_Thinking_and_Programming">Probabilistic Thinking and Programming Notebook</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="connecting-with-the-community" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="connecting-with-the-community">Connecting with the Community</h2>
<p>One of the highlights for me was meeting the dynamic duo behind our practical lab—James and Kira. Their hard work and dedication to organizing these sessions were evident, and it was great to share insights and ideas with James from DeepMind and Kira from UCL. We even managed to capture a memorable moment together, which I’ll cherish as a reminder of this wonderful experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="engaging-talks-on-fairness-and-speech-recognition" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="engaging-talks-on-fairness-and-speech-recognition">Engaging Talks on Fairness and Speech Recognition</h2>
<p>With so many sessions happening concurrently, choosing which ones to attend was a challenge! I was fortunate enough to participate in two deeply insightful presentations. The first was on fairness in machine learning algorithms, a critical topic that delved into how we can ensure AI systems are fair, ethical, and inclusive. The second presentation focused on automatic speech recognition for low-resource languages, showcasing groundbreaking work that aims to bridge the digital divide and make AI accessible to all communities, regardless of linguistic diversity.</p>
</section>
<section id="celebrating-the-start-of-an-inspiring-week" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="celebrating-the-start-of-an-inspiring-week">Celebrating the Start of an Inspiring Week</h2>
<p>We capped off the day with a vibrant celebration, marking the official start of the Deep Learning Indaba 2024. The energy was infectious, and it was a fantastic way to unwind and connect with fellow AI enthusiasts from different parts of the continent.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Reflecting on Day 1, I’m filled with gratitude and excitement. It’s truly an honor to be part of such a passionate and forward-thinking community. The discussions, learning, and networking have already been incredible, and I can’t wait to see what the rest of the week has in store.</p>
<p>Stay tuned for more updates, reflections, and possibly pictures from this inspiring event! 📸</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-01/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dli-24-day-01/indaba.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Understanding Responsible AI: A Deep Dive into Ethical AI Development</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/responsible-ai/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) is rapidly advancing, transforming industries from healthcare to transportation. With its growing influence, there is an increasing need to ensure that AI is developed and deployed responsibly. This is where Responsible AI (RAI) comes in—a framework designed to guide the ethical use of AI, ensuring fairness, transparency, accountability, and respect for human rights. In this article, I explore the key concepts of Responsible AI, its importance, and how organizations can implement strategies that align AI development with ethical principles.</p>
<p>This article is primarily a summary of the content I learnt in the course <a href="https://app.datacamp.com/learn/courses/responsible-ai-practices">Responsible AI Practices</a> on DataCamp. I enrolled in this course after I had the privilege of reviewing the notebooks for the Responsible AI practicals for the upcoming Deep Learning Indaba 2024 in Dakar, Senegal. This combination of learning and practical experience has given me a well-rounded perspective on the principles of Responsible AI, which I am excited to share. I must also thank Arewa Data Science Academy for giving me the opportunity to enjoy a Data Camp scholarship, which allowed me to learn several concepts and earn relevant certifications for free.</p>
<section id="defining-responsible-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="defining-responsible-ai">Defining Responsible AI</h2>
<p>Responsible AI refers to the practice of designing, developing, and deploying AI systems with an understanding of their ethical implications and societal impacts. It is about ensuring that AI systems are fair, transparent, accountable, and respectful of privacy and human rights. The goal is to create AI that benefits society without causing harm, focusing not only on the technology itself but also on the values guiding its use.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-responsible-ai-is-crucial" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-responsible-ai-is-crucial">Why Responsible AI is Crucial</h2>
<p>AI’s ability to process vast amounts of data and learn from it is revolutionizing fields like healthcare, education, and finance. However, these advancements come with risks. AI can perpetuate biases, invade privacy, or be used unethically if not developed responsibly. For example, facial recognition systems have been found to have higher error rates for people of color, leading to discriminatory outcomes. Similarly, automated hiring systems can reflect and amplify existing biases in the data they are trained on.</p>
<p>These risks highlight the need for Responsible AI practices that mitigate negative impacts and promote fairness and inclusivity. The stakes are high, making Responsible AI a critical aspect of any AI development strategy.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-principles-of-responsible-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-principles-of-responsible-ai">Key Principles of Responsible AI</h2>
<p>The principles of Responsible AI are based on globally recognized guidelines, such as those from the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD). Key principles include:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Transparency and Explainability: AI systems should be designed so that their decisions can be understood and explained.</li>
<li>Fairness and Non-Discrimination: AI should be free from biases and discrimination, promoting inclusivity and equity.</li>
<li>Robustness and Safety: AI systems must be reliable, secure, and capable of operating safely in various conditions.</li>
<li>Privacy and Data Governance: AI should respect privacy and ensure secure data handling.</li>
<li>Accountability: Organizations should be accountable for the outcomes of their AI systems.</li>
<li>Inclusive Growth and Sustainability: AI should bridge digital divides and contribute to sustainable development.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="responsible-ai-vs.-ai-ethics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="responsible-ai-vs.-ai-ethics">Responsible AI vs.&nbsp;AI Ethics</h2>
<p>While Responsible AI and AI Ethics are closely related, they are not identical. AI Ethics focuses broadly on the philosophical and moral questions surrounding AI, while Responsible AI is more practical, emphasizing the implementation of ethical considerations in measurable ways. It involves using clear metrics and frameworks to ensure that AI systems align with ethical principles.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-global-regulatory-landscape" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-global-regulatory-landscape">The Global Regulatory Landscape</h2>
<p>Regulation of AI is still evolving, but several regions are leading the way. The European Union’s AI Act classifies AI systems based on risk levels and imposes stringent requirements on high-risk applications. In the United States, initiatives like the AI Bill of Rights and various state-level regulations are shaping AI governance. Countries like Canada, the UK, and China are also developing frameworks tailored to their societal and economic needs.</p>
<p>These regulatory efforts share a common goal: to protect human rights while fostering innovation in AI. As AI technology continues to advance, these regulations will play a critical role in ensuring that AI systems are used responsibly.</p>
</section>
<section id="implementing-responsible-ai-an-8-step-approach" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implementing-responsible-ai-an-8-step-approach">Implementing Responsible AI: An 8-Step Approach</h2>
<p>For organizations looking to implement Responsible AI, the following eight-step approach is recommended:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Embrace AI Governance: Secure organizational commitment to align AI development with ethical standards and business goals.</li>
<li>Build an AI Playbook: Develop a strategic plan that documents AI governance practices, keeping it flexible and up to date.</li>
<li>Identify Key Stakeholders: Engage both internal and external stakeholders to ensure inclusivity and address diverse perspectives.</li>
<li>Leverage Internal Support Mechanisms: Use ethics boards, training programs, and AI squads to guide ethical AI development.</li>
<li>Embrace a Multi-Stakeholder Approach: Include community members, industry experts, and policymakers in AI governance.</li>
<li>Explore Additional Responsible Behavior Indicators: Demonstrate a commitment to Responsible AI through certifications, CSR standards, and transparent ESG reporting.</li>
<li>Implement Governance Tools: Develop guidelines and procedures that uphold Responsible AI principles.</li>
<li>Monitor, Audit, and Evaluate AI Systems: Continuously monitor and audit AI systems to ensure they remain aligned with ethical standards.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="the-importance-of-diversity-in-ai-development" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-importance-of-diversity-in-ai-development">The Importance of Diversity in AI Development</h2>
<p>Diversity, equity, and inclusion (DE&amp;I) are essential for creating fair and unbiased AI systems. A lack of diversity in AI development teams can lead to systems that reflect and reinforce societal biases. For instance, facial recognition systems and hiring algorithms have been shown to produce biased results when developed without diverse perspectives.</p>
<p>Research shows that diverse teams are more innovative and perform better. Prioritizing DE&amp;I in AI development is not just ethically sound but also beneficial for business, leading to more robust and inclusive AI solutions.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-the-path-forward-for-responsible-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-the-path-forward-for-responsible-ai">Conclusion: The Path Forward for Responsible AI</h2>
<p>Responsible AI is a continuous journey that requires ongoing evaluation, monitoring, and adaptation. My recent experience reviewing content for the upcoming Deep Learning Indaba 2024 reinforced the importance of this topic. The principles I learned in the DataCamp course on Responsible AI practices, coupled with my practical experience, have deepened my understanding of the need for ethical AI governance.</p>
<p>As AI continues to evolve, it is our collective responsibility to guide its development in ways that reflect our highest ethical standards. By embracing Responsible AI principles, we can ensure that AI serves humanity in a way that is fair, transparent, and accountable, ultimately contributing to a more equitable and sustainable future.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning indaba</category>
  <category>responsible ai</category>
  <category>datacamp</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/responsible-ai/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/responsible-ai/responsible-ai.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="83" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Persistence: How 365 Days of Consistency Transformed My Learning Journey</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/forum-devotee/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>After 365 consecutive days of active participation, I’m thrilled to announce that I’ve achieved Devotee status on the DeepLearning.AI forum. This milestone is more than just a badge—it shows the power of unwavering commitment and the compound effect of daily habits.</p>
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/forum-devotee/devotee.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The journey to Devotee status is as unforgiving as it is rewarding. Missing even a single day means starting over from scratch. Imagine the dedication required to maintain this streak for an entire year, knowing that a momentary lapse on day 364 would reset your progress to zero. It’s this level of consistency that separates casual participants from true devotees.</p>
<p>My path to this achievement began with smaller milestones: the 10-day Enthusiast badge, followed by the 100-day Aficionado badge. Each step reinforced my commitment and built momentum towards the ultimate goal. Now, as only the fifth person in over four years to reach Devotee status, I find myself in the company of the forum’s most dedicated members.</p>
<p>But this streak is just one facet of a larger commitment to personal growth through consistent effort. Parallel to my DeepLearning.AI journey, I’m maintaining a 196-day streak on DataCamp and a 261 day streak on GitHub. These aren’t just numbers; they represent a fundamental shift in how I approach learning and self-improvement.</p>
<p>The concept of “atomic habits,” popularized by James Clear, has been instrumental in my approach. The idea is simple yet powerful: tiny, consistent changes accumulate over time, leading to significant personal transformation. By showing up every day, even when motivation wanes, I’m not just learning new skills—I’m reshaping my identity into someone who pursues growth relentlessly.</p>
<p>This journey has taught me several valuable lessons:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Consistency trumps intensity: Small, daily efforts are more impactful than sporadic bursts of activity.</p></li>
<li><p>Progress compounds: What seems like slow progress early on accelerates as habits become ingrained.</p></li>
<li><p>Identity-based habits stick: By viewing myself as a “lifelong learner,” maintaining these streaks becomes natural.</p></li>
<li><p>Community matters: The DeepLearning.AI forum and other platforms provide accountability and support.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Moving forward, I’m committed to channeling my energy into endeavors that contribute to my professional and personal growth. This means setting ambitious targets, minimizing distractions like excessive social media use, and continuously reassessing my habits to ensure they align with my long-term goals.</p>
<p>As I reflect on this achievement, I’m filled with gratitude for the guidance and opportunities that have brought me here. I’m also excited about the future, knowing that the habits I’ve built will serve as a foundation for even greater accomplishments.</p>
<p>To those embarking on their own journey of consistent self-improvement, remember: every day is an opportunity to take a step forward. The path may be challenging, but the rewards—in knowledge gained, skills developed, and personal growth achieved—are immeasurable.</p>
<p>Alhamdulillah for this milestone, and may Allah continue to guide and bless our efforts towards meaningful growth and contribution.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/forum-devotee/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/forum-devotee/devotee.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="99" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Journey from Learner to Leader: My Deep Learning.AI and Coursera Adventure</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-mentor/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On August 14, 2024, I reached a significant milestone in my AI career: I was officially designated as a mentor for the TensorFlow Developer Certificate program on Deep Learning.AI and Coursera. This comprehensive certification, consisting of four courses, introduces learners to the powerful TensorFlow framework. As I reflect on this achievement, I’m filled with pride and gratitude for how far I’ve come in such a short time.</p>
<section id="the-tensorflow-developer-professional-certificate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-tensorflow-developer-professional-certificate">The TensorFlow Developer Professional Certificate</h2>
<p>The certificate program I now mentor comprises four essential courses:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, and Deep Learning</li>
<li>Convolutional Neural Networks in TensorFlow</li>
<li>Natural Language Processing in TensorFlow</li>
<li>Sequences, Time Series and Prediction</li>
</ol>
<p>These courses cover a broad spectrum of AI applications, from basic neural networks to advanced techniques in computer vision, natural language processing, and time series analysis.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-serendipitous-beginning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-serendipitous-beginning">A Serendipitous Beginning</h2>
<p>My AI learning journey began with the Arewa Data Science Academy fellowship, a program that holds a special place in my heart. Simultaneously, I embarked on Andrew Ng’s Machine Learning Specialization on Coursera. This coincidence set the stage for my rapid progression in the AI community.</p>
</section>
<section id="rising-through-the-ranks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rising-through-the-ranks">Rising Through the Ranks</h2>
<p>My involvement with Deep Learning.AI and Coursera deepened quickly:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Forum Moderator:</strong> In November 2023, just a few months into my journey, I became a moderator at the DeepLearning.AI forum, helping to guide discussions and support learners tackling challenges in various courses offered in the community.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Course Tester:</strong> I was invited to be part of the testing group for a major course upgrade, partly due to my active contribution as a moderator, where we transitioned from an older version of TensorFlow to the cutting-edge TensorFlow 2.16. My insightful feedback contributed to refining the course content and user experience across all four courses.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-mentor/tester.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mentor:</strong> The crowning achievement came in August 2024, when I was offered the opportunity to become a mentor for the TensorFlow Developer Certificate courses, in addition to my moderator role. This position allows me to guide learners through the intricacies of TensorFlow, from basic concepts to advanced applications in CNN, NLP, and time series prediction.</li>
</ul>
<p>This rapid transition from learner to contributor to mentor and moderator has been both humbling and exhilarating.</p>
</section>
<section id="celebrating-milestones-and-looking-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="celebrating-milestones-and-looking-ahead">Celebrating Milestones and Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>As I continue to contribute to the AI community, I’m committed to making a lasting impact in all the places I volunteer, especially at Arewa Data Science Academy, where my journey began. Each step forward reminds me of the importance of celebrating small victories while keeping an eye on future goals.</p>
<p>My new role as a TensorFlow Developer Certificate mentor, alongside my moderator responsibilities, is not just a personal achievement; it’s an opportunity to give back to the community that has nurtured my growth. It’s a chance to inspire and guide the next generation of AI enthusiasts and developers across various domains of machine learning and deep learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-message-to-aspiring-ai-developers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-message-to-aspiring-ai-developers">A Message to Aspiring AI Developers</h2>
<p>As I forge ahead in pursuing my dreams in the AI field, I’m reminded of the power of persistence, continuous learning, and community support. To all aspiring AI developers out there: keep pushing, keep learning, and remember that today’s learner can be tomorrow’s leader.</p>
<p>The path from novice to mentor can be shorter than you think. With dedication and the right opportunities, you can quickly find yourself in a position to guide others. Embrace every chance to learn, contribute, and grow within the AI community.</p>
<p>Here’s to the journey ahead, filled with neural networks, convolutional layers, natural language models, time series predictions, and the endless possibilities of artificial intelligence!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>tensorflow</category>
  <category>arewads</category>
  <category>deeplearning-ai</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-mentor/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-mentor/mentor-mail.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="91" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Contribution to Quarto-web: A Small Edit with a Big Impact</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/contributing-to-quarto/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>I’m thrilled to share my recent experience contributing to the Quarto-web open-source project. Although it might seem like a small change, my contribution aimed to improve the clarity and readability of the documentation, ensuring users have a smoother experience when learning about Quarto. I’ve always appreciated Quarto since I first learned about it from <a href="https://shmuhammadd.github.io/">Dr.&nbsp;Shamsuddeen Muhammad</a> during the first cohort of the Arewa Data Science Fellowship. I continued practicing, and now I am proudly a contributor. I look forward to making more impactful contributions in the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="spotting-the-issue-a-simple-typo-and-punctuation-fix" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="spotting-the-issue-a-simple-typo-and-punctuation-fix">Spotting the Issue: A Simple Typo and Punctuation Fix</h2>
<p>While exploring the Quarto Dashboards documentation, specifically the <code>R Graphics</code> section tip on this <a href="https://quarto.org/docs/dashboards/data-display.html">page</a>, I noticed a minor typo—‘than’ was mistakenly written as ‘that’. Additionally, there were a few missing commas, which could potentially confuse readers.</p>
<p>These might seem like minor issues, but clear and accurate documentation is crucial in helping users understand and utilize software tools effectively. I decided to take action and correct these mistakes to enhance the user experience.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-pull-request-a-quick-fix" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-pull-request-a-quick-fix">The Pull Request: A Quick Fix</h2>
<p>I submitted a pull request (#1214) to update the _plots-interactive.md file, which contained the typo and punctuation errors. The changes were straightforward:</p>
<ul>
<li>Corrected the typo from ‘that’ to ‘than’.</li>
<li>Added a few missing commas for better clarity and readability.</li>
</ul>
<p>These edits were minor but important, as they helped ensure the documentation was accurate and easy to follow.</p>
</section>
<section id="merged-and-celebrated-the-joy-of-contributing" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="merged-and-celebrated-the-joy-of-contributing">Merged and Celebrated: The Joy of Contributing</h2>
<p>To my delight, my pull request was reviewed and merged by the maintainers. You can view the merged changes in the pull request <a href="https://github.com/quarto-dev/quarto-web/pull/1214">here</a>. It was a small contribution, but seeing my changes go live was incredibly rewarding. It was a reminder that even small contributions can make a big difference in the open-source community.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-on-my-contribution" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-on-my-contribution">Reflections on My Contribution</h2>
<p>This experience has taught me a few valuable lessons:</p>
<ul>
<li>Attention to Detail Matters: Even small errors in documentation can lead to misunderstandings. Taking the time to correct them helps improve the overall quality of the project.</li>
<li>Every Contribution Counts: No matter the size, every contribution to an open-source project helps make it better. It’s about being part of a community effort.</li>
<li>Learning and Growing: This was my first contribution to Quarto-web, and it has encouraged me to continue participating in open-source projects. There’s always something new to learn and areas to improve.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="looking-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>
<p>I’m excited to continue exploring opportunities in the open-source world. Whether it’s fixing typos, adding features, or writing documentation, every bit helps the community grow and thrive. If you’re interested in getting involved, I encourage you to look for ways to contribute, no matter how small they may seem.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading, and feel free to follow me on the social media links in my about page. Happy coding!</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>quarto</category>
  <category>quarto-web</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/contributing-to-quarto/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/contributing-to-quarto/contribution.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="92" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Metrics for Medical Diagnosis Evaluation</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/medical-eval/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Medical diagnosis is a multifaceted endeavour that relies on a comprehensive assessment of various factors, including symptoms, tests, and medical history. Conditional probability, which calculates the likelihood of an event occurring given another event, plays a pivotal role in evaluating the effectiveness of medical diagnoses. In the context of healthcare, this involves estimating the probability of a patient having a disease, given that they have tested positive for it.</p>
</section>
<section id="understanding-accuracy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understanding-accuracy">Understanding Accuracy</h2>
<p>One of the most commonly used metrics in medical diagnosis is accuracy. It gauges the overall proportion of accurate diagnoses, derived from correctly identifying patients with or without a specific ailment. Accuracy can be mathematically expressed as a combination of sensitivity and specificity, both of which are vital metrics.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Accuracy%20=%20Sensitivity%20%5Ctimes%20Prevalence%20+%20Specificity%20%5Ctimes%20(1%20-%20Prevalence)"></p>
</section>
<section id="sensitivity-and-specificity" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sensitivity-and-specificity">Sensitivity and Specificity</h2>
<p>Sensitivity measures the ability of a diagnostic method or model to correctly identify patients who have the disease, while specificity measures its ability to accurately identify those without the disease. These metrics can also be understood in terms of conditional probabilities, simplifying them to the probability of a positive or negative test result given a patient’s disease status.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Sensitivity%20=%20%5Cdfrac%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,positive%5C,and%5C,disease%7D%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,disease%7D"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Specificity%20=%20%5Cdfrac%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,negative%5C,and%5C,normal%7D%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,normal%7D"></p>
<p>In terms of conditional probabilities:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Sensitivity%20=%20P(positive%7Cdisease)"> <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Specificity%20=%20P(negative%7Cnormal)"></p>
</section>
<section id="positive-predictive-value-and-negative-predictive-value" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="positive-predictive-value-and-negative-predictive-value">Positive Predictive Value and Negative Predictive Value</h2>
<p>To assess the likelihood of a patient having or not having the disease based on their test results, we employ positive predictive value (PPV) and negative predictive value (NPV). These metrics provide insight into the probabilities of disease presence or absence given a positive or negative test result, respectively. This is more useful and practical than just sensitivity and specificity</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?PPV%20=%20%5Cdfrac%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,positive%5C,and%5C,disease%7D%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,positive%7D"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?NPV%20=%20%5Cdfrac%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,negative%5C,and%5C,normal%7D%7B%5C,number%5C,of%5C,negative%7D"></p>
<section id="leveraging-bayes-rule" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leveraging-bayes-rule">Leveraging Bayes’ Rule:</h3>
<p>To calculate PPV and NPV, Bayes’ rule, a formula relating conditional probabilities, is employed. This rule offers a nuanced perspective by taking into account sensitivity, specificity, and prevalence—the proportion of patients with the disease in the population.</p>
<p>Using conditional probabilities, we write:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?PPV%20=%20P(disease%7Cpositive)"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?NPV%20=%20P(normal%7Cnegative)"></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="confusion-matrix" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="confusion-matrix">Confusion Matrix</h2>
<p>A confusion matrix serves as a valuable tool to visualize the performance of a diagnostic method or model. It displays true positives, true negatives, false positives, and false negatives for different thresholds or cut-off points, which can be adjusted to modify the diagnostic performance metrics.</p>
<p>A confusion matrix can be represented as:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>Positive</th>
<th>Negative</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Disease</td>
<td>TP</td>
<td>FN</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Normal</td>
<td>FP</td>
<td>TN</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>where: TP = True Positives (number of)</p>
<p>FP = False Positives</p>
<p>FN = False Negatives</p>
<p>TN = True Negatives</p>
</section>
<section id="precision-and-recall" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="precision-and-recall">Precision and Recall</h2>
<p>Precision measures the proportion of correctly identified positive test results, while recall assesses the proportion of patients with the disease that are accurately identified. These metrics are also synonymous with positive predictive value (PPV) and sensitivity, respectively.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Precision%20=%20%5Cdfrac%7BTP%7D%7BTP+FP%7D"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Recall%20=%20%5Cdfrac%7BTP%7D%7BTP+FN%7D"></p>
<p>Precision and recall are also known as positive predictive value (PPV) and sensitivity, respectively. Therefore, they are equivalent to:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Precision%20=%20PPR"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Recall%20=%20Sensitivity"></p>
</section>
<section id="f1-score" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="f1-score">F1-Score</h2>
<p>The F1-score combines precision and recall into a single metric, which is the harmonic mean of both values. This metric is also known as the Dice coefficient score, reflecting the similarity between two sets.</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?F1%5C,Score%20%20=%202%20%5Ctimes%20%5Cdfrac%7BPR%7D%7BP+R%7D"></p>
</section>
<section id="evaluating-diagnostic-methods-with-roc-curves" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="evaluating-diagnostic-methods-with-roc-curves">Evaluating Diagnostic Methods with ROC Curves</h2>
<p>To compare different diagnostic methods or models, the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve is a valuable tool. It illustrates the trade-off between sensitivity and specificity at varying thresholds. A high-performing diagnostic method or model should yield a ROC curve closely resembling the top-left corner of the plot, with the area under the ROC curve (AUC) indicating its overall performance.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/medical-eval/roc_curve.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>ROC Curve</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The multifaceted landscape of medical diagnosis evaluation encompasses a spectrum of metrics and tools. Understanding these metrics and their mathematical underpinnings is crucial for accurately assessing the performance of diagnostic methods and models in healthcare.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>evaluation metrics</category>
  <category>medical diagnosis</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/medical-eval/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastering Data Structures and Algorithms on Coursera</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dsa-algorithms-cert/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I am thrilled to announce that I have successfully completed the <strong>Foundations of Algorithms and Data Structures Specialization</strong> offered by the University of Colorado Boulder on Coursera. The specialization was excellently taught by Professor Sriram Sankaranarayanan and spanned five comprehensive courses. I embarked on this journey last year, and it has been an enriching experience.</p>
<section id="course-overview-and-learnings" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="course-overview-and-learnings">Course Overview and Learnings</h2>
<section id="algorithms-for-searching-sorting-and-indexing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="algorithms-for-searching-sorting-and-indexing">1. Algorithms for Searching, Sorting, and Indexing</h3>
<p>This course laid the foundation for algorithm design and analysis. It covered:</p>
<ul>
<li>Basics of algorithm design and analysis</li>
<li>Sorting arrays</li>
<li>Data structures such as priority queues and hash functions</li>
<li>Applications like Bloom filters</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="trees-and-graphs-basics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="trees-and-graphs-basics">2. Trees and Graphs: Basics</h3>
<p>This course delved into tree and graph data structures. Key topics included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Basic algorithms on tree data structures</li>
<li>Binary search trees and self-balancing trees</li>
<li>Graph data structures and traversal algorithms</li>
<li>Advanced topics like kd-trees for spatial data and algorithms for spatial data</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="dynamic-programming-and-greedy-algorithms" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dynamic-programming-and-greedy-algorithms">3. Dynamic Programming and Greedy Algorithms</h3>
<p>In this course, I learned essential algorithm design techniques, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Divide and conquer</li>
<li>Dynamic programming</li>
<li>Greedy algorithms</li>
<li>Introduction to intractability (NP-completeness)</li>
<li>Using linear/integer programming solvers for optimization problems</li>
<li>Advanced topics in data structures</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="approximate-algorithms-and-linear-programming" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="approximate-algorithms-and-linear-programming">4. Approximate Algorithms and Linear Programming</h3>
<p>This course focused on:</p>
<ul>
<li>Linear and integer programming formulations for solving algorithmic problems</li>
<li>Applications in resource allocation, scheduling, task assignment, and the traveling salesperson problem</li>
<li>Algorithms for NP-hard problems with guaranteed approximation factors</li>
<li>Efficient algorithms providing useful bounds on optimal solutions</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="advanced-data-structures-rsa-and-quantum-algorithms" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="advanced-data-structures-rsa-and-quantum-algorithms">5. Advanced Data Structures, RSA, and Quantum Algorithms</h3>
<p>The final course introduced:</p>
<ul>
<li>Number-theory based cryptography</li>
<li>Basics of quantum algorithms</li>
<li>Advanced data structures like B-Trees and Suffix Tries</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Completing this specialization has been a significant milestone in my Data Science and Machine Learning/AI journey. I am excited to apply the knowledge and skills I have gained to future projects and challenges.</p>
<p>I highly recommend this specialization to anyone looking to deepen their understanding of algorithms and data structures. The courses are well-structured, and Professor Sriram Sankaranarayanan’s teaching is both clear and engaging.</p>
<p>I look forward to what the future holds and I am eager to continue my learning journey in the ever-evolving field of Data Science and AI.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>data structures</category>
  <category>algorithms</category>
  <category>data science</category>
  <category>programming</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dsa-algorithms-cert/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/dsa-algorithms-cert/dls-cert.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="113" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Journey in Deep Learning: From TensorFlow to PyTorch and Back</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-dev/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I recently completed the <code>DeepLearning.AI</code> TensorFlow Developer Professional Certificate, a milestone that marked a significant step in my deep learning journey. My exploration of TensorFlow began last year while taking the second course of the DeepLearning.AI Deep Learning Specialization, excellently taught by Andrew Ng.</p>
<p>Following my initial foray into TensorFlow, I delved extensively into PyTorch during the Arewa Data Science Academy’s Deep Learning with PyTorch fellowship. The allure of PyTorch, with its state-of-the-art (SOTA) models, pythonic nature and high customizability, made me somewhat hesitant to further pursue TensorFlow. However, an unexpected opportunity arose when, as a moderator in the DeepLearning.AI Forum, I was invited to test a TensorFlow course. This experience reignited my interest and ultimately led me to pursue the Professional Certificate on Coursera.</p>
<p>Contrary to my initial reservations, I found TensorFlow to be quite user-friendly. While it may offer less customization compared to PyTorch, TensorFlow’s learning curve is significantly gentler, making it accessible to a wider audience.</p>
<p>The TensorFlow Developer Professional Certificate comprises four courses, each designed to quickly get learners up to speed with TensorFlow:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, and Deep Learning</li>
<li>Convolutional Neural Networks in TensorFlow</li>
<li>Natural Language Processing in TensorFlow</li>
<li>Sequences, Time Series, and Prediction</li>
</ol>
<p>The certificate is excellently taught by Laurence Moroney, who leads AI Advocacy at Google. His vision is to make AI easy for developers and widen access to machine learning careers for everyone. Laurence is a prolific author, with dozens of programming books to his name, including ‘AI and ML for Coders’ at O’Reilly. He is also an active member of the Science Fiction Writers of America, having authored several sci-fi novels, comic books, and a produced screenplay.</p>
<p>Throughout the series of courses, I built on my existing TensorFlow skills, learning about regular dense layers, convolutional neural networks (CNNs), recurrent neural networks (RNNs), long short-term memory networks (LSTMs), gated recurrent units (GRUs), and more. I even explored lambda layers in TensorFlow. The culmination of the course involved applying deep learning and sequence models to time series data.</p>
<p>Completing this course has been an immensely rewarding experience. I am grateful to Coursera for providing a 90% discount, making it possible for me to embark on and complete this learning journey. The structured learning path and the expertise of the instructors have significantly enhanced my understanding and proficiency in using TensorFlow.</p>
<p>In conclusion, while my journey began with PyTorch, the experience with TensorFlow has been equally enriching. TensorFlow’s ease of use and comprehensive learning resources have made it a valuable tool in my deep learning toolkit. I am excited to apply these skills in future projects and continue exploring the evolving landscape of deep learning technologies.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tensorflow</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>deep learning</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-dev/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/tensorflow-dev/tensorflow-cert.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="118" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PyTorch for Natural Language Processing</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/pytorch-nlp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In the dynamic field of Natural Language Processing (NLP), the quest for more robust and scalable models has led researchers and developers towards powerful, flexible tools that can handle the complexity and size of modern datasets. One such tool that has risen to prominence is PyTorch. Developed by Facebook’s AI Research lab, PyTorch offers a compelling blend of flexibility, speed, and ease of use, making it an ideal choice for NLP tasks. Having recently completed a track on DataCamp on NLP with PyTorch, I find it useful to pen down how PyTorch changes the game.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-pytorch" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-pytorch">What is PyTorch?</h2>
<p>PyTorch is an open-source machine learning library based on the Torch library, widely recognized for its simplicity and interface clarity. It excels in areas requiring automatic differentiation and dynamic neural networks, particularly in complex, evolving projects where versatility is as critical as performance. This is largely attributed to its use of dynamic computation graphs (called “define-by-run” schema), which allow changes to be made on-the-fly and graphs to be built during runtime.</p>
</section>
<section id="pytorchs-advantages-for-nlp" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pytorchs-advantages-for-nlp">PyTorch’s Advantages for NLP</h2>
<p>The characteristics of PyTorch particularly beneficial for NLP include its intuitive design, ease of debugging, and seamless integration with the Python programming environment. Unlike static graphs, which need to define and optimize the entire model architecture before running, PyTorch’s dynamic graphs enable developers to alter their models as inputs change, which is especially useful for the varying sequence lengths in text data.</p>
<section id="flexibility-and-ease-of-use" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="flexibility-and-ease-of-use">Flexibility and Ease of Use</h3>
<p>For NLP, models often need to experiment with novel ideas or hybrid architectures, and PyTorch’s flexibility ensures that researchers can implement changes almost as quickly as they can think of them. It integrates seamlessly with the Python data science stack, making it easier to turn research prototypes into production-ready code.</p>
</section>
<section id="rich-prebuilt-libraries" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rich-prebuilt-libraries">Rich Prebuilt Libraries</h3>
<p>PyTorch is supported by a rich ecosystem of libraries and extensions. Libraries such as torchtext simplify text processing and provide utilities for common tasks like tokenization, vocabulary creation, and sequence padding, allowing researchers to handle preprocessing efficiently and focus more on model development.</p>
</section>
<section id="torchtext-for-streamlined-text-preprocessing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="torchtext-for-streamlined-text-preprocessing">torchtext for Streamlined Text Preprocessing</h3>
<p>A key component in PyTorch’s NLP capabilities is torchtext, a library designed to streamline preprocessing pipelines. torchtext offers utilities for batch processing of text, making it easier to load and handle large datasets efficiently. With functionalities such as built-in vocabularies, pre-trained word vectors, and support for common datasets, torchtext significantly reduces the boilerplate code required in text preprocessing. This allows developers to rapidly experiment with different NLP models and techniques, enhancing productivity and innovation.</p>
</section>
<section id="community-and-support" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-and-support">Community and Support</h3>
<p>The PyTorch community is a vibrant and growing ecosystem. With extensive documentation, tutorials, and forums, developers and researchers can easily find help and resources. The community not only contributes to the core library but also continuously adds to a growing repository of models and tools, which accelerates development and fosters innovation in NLP.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="pytorch-in-action-nlp-applications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pytorch-in-action-nlp-applications">PyTorch in Action: NLP Applications</h2>
<p>In NLP, PyTorch has been used to achieve state-of-the-art results in several areas:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Text Classification: PyTorch provides a straightforward approach for developing models for sentiment analysis, topic classification, and more.</li>
<li>Machine Translation: The flexibility in sequence-to-sequence models, attention mechanisms, and memory networks has made PyTorch a popular choice for researchers working on language translation applications.</li>
<li>Language Modeling and Generation: PyTorch supports advanced models like Transformers and GPT-n series, which are crucial for tasks that require understanding context and generating text.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>PyTorch’s impact on NLP is undeniable. Its design inherently supports the rapid prototyping and iterative refinement that NLP models often require. Whether you’re a seasoned data scientist or a novice in machine learning, PyTorch provides the tools to innovate and scale NLP applications effectively. As NLP continues to evolve, PyTorch’s role in driving forward the boundaries of what machines understand about human language is likely only to grow, making it an invaluable asset in any NLP developer’s toolkit.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>arewads</category>
  <category>pytorch</category>
  <category>nlp</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/pytorch-nlp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Journey to Becoming a Professional Data Scientist: A DataCamp Certification Odyssey</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/datacamp-cert/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Embarking on the path to deepen my data science expertise, I was presented with an invaluable opportunity—a free premium subscription to DataCamp, courtesy of Arewa Data Science Academy. This opportunity was not just a stepping stone but a gateway to a broader horizon in data science that I eagerly embraced.</p>
<p>The journey commenced with the Associate Data Scientist with Python track. Given my foundational knowledge and previous encounter with DataCamp’s Introduction to Python course, I was not venturing into uncharted territory. This familiarity served me well, enabling me to swiftly navigate through the coursework and complete the entire track within a week.</p>
<p>But the quest for knowledge is insatiable. I ventured further into the realm of data manipulation and retrieval by tackling the revamped SQL Fundamentals track. This was followed by successfully achieving the Associate Data Scientist with SQL certification, marking another milestone in my journey.</p>
<p>Eager to delve deeper, I enrolled in the Data Scientist with Python track. This comprehensive curriculum was not just about Python; it integrated SQL courses and introduced vital skills in package writing and Git fundamentals. This holistic approach equipped me with a robust set of tools and knowledge, preparing me for the pinnacle of my journey—the Professional Data Scientist Certification.</p>
<p>The certification process was rigorous, encompassing two timed written exams that tested my theoretical understanding through multiple-choice and fill-in-the-blank questions. However, the real challenge lay in the practical data science exam, which required me to code machine learning models and present my findings via webcam. This phase tested not just my technical skills but also my ability to communicate complex results effectively.</p>
<p>Despite the pressure and the initial setback in the practical exam—stemming from difficulties in data cleaning—I remained undeterred. After a period of diligent study and review, I reattempted the practical exam. With renewed confidence and enhanced skills, I passed on my second attempt.</p>
<p>This journey was demanding, yet immensely rewarding. It culminated in earning a certificate that not only represents a testament to my skills and dedication but also empowers me with credentials recognized for two years.</p>
<p>Reflecting on this experience, I am reminded of the importance of resilience, the value of continuous learning, and the doors that can open when one is willing to push through challenges. My journey to becoming a professional data scientist was not just about acquiring a certificate; it was about growth, perseverance, and the relentless pursuit of excellence in the ever-evolving field of data science.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>arewads</category>
  <category>datacamp</category>
  <category>dcdonates</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/datacamp-cert/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/datacamp-cert/datacamp.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="83" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Harnessing the Power of R Shiny for Interactive Data Visualization</title>
  <dc:creator>Lukman Aliyu Jibril</dc:creator>
  <link>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/first-shiny/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction:</h2>
<p>In the realm of data science and statistical computing, R has long been a staple for analysts and researchers. However, the R ecosystem extends far beyond static analyses and plots, entering the dynamic world of web applications with R Shiny. This powerful framework allows users to build interactive web applications directly from R, enabling end-users to interact with their data analyses and visualizations in real-time.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-is-r-shiny" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-r-shiny">What is R Shiny?</h2>
<p>R Shiny is an R package that makes it straightforward to build interactive web apps straight from R. Without needing to know HTML, CSS, or JavaScript, data scientists can create applications that allow users to interact with their data, change parameters, and visualize the results instantly.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-features-of-r-shiny" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-features-of-r-shiny">Key Features of R Shiny:</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Interactivity: Users can interact with the application, altering inputs and immediately seeing the output change.</p></li>
<li><p>Accessibility: Shiny apps can be hosted on a webpage, making your R analysis accessible to anyone with internet access.</p></li>
<li><p>Customization: While Shiny makes it easy to get started with default settings, it also allows for extensive customization for more advanced users.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="getting-started-with-r-shiny" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="getting-started-with-r-shiny">Getting Started with R Shiny:</h2>
<p>To begin, you need to install the Shiny package from CRAN:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">install.packages</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"shiny"</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>Then, you can create a simple Shiny app with just a few lines of code:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(shiny)</span>
<span id="cb2-2"></span>
<span id="cb2-3"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Define UI for application</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4">ui <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">fluidPage</span>(</span>
<span id="cb2-5">   <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">titlePanel</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"My First Shiny App"</span>),</span>
<span id="cb2-6">   <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sidebarLayout</span>(</span>
<span id="cb2-7">      <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sidebarPanel</span>(</span>
<span id="cb2-8">         <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sliderInput</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"num"</span>, </span>
<span id="cb2-9">                     <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Choose a number:"</span>, </span>
<span id="cb2-10">                     <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">min =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, </span>
<span id="cb2-11">                     <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">max =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">100</span>, </span>
<span id="cb2-12">                     <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">value =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">50</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-13">      ),</span>
<span id="cb2-14">      <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mainPanel</span>(</span>
<span id="cb2-15">         <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">textOutput</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"selectedNum"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-16">      )</span>
<span id="cb2-17">   )</span>
<span id="cb2-18">)</span>
<span id="cb2-19"></span>
<span id="cb2-20"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Define server logic</span></span>
<span id="cb2-21">server <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(input, output) {</span>
<span id="cb2-22">   output<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>selectedNum <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">renderText</span>({ </span>
<span id="cb2-23">       <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"You selected"</span>, input<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>num)</span>
<span id="cb2-24">   })</span>
<span id="cb2-25">}</span>
<span id="cb2-26"></span>
<span id="cb2-27"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Run the application </span></span>
<span id="cb2-28"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">shinyApp</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ui =</span> ui, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">server =</span> server)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>This app creates a slider for the user to select a number and immediately displays the selected number on the screen.</p>
</section>
<section id="challenges-and-limitations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-and-limitations">Challenges and Limitations:</h2>
<p>While R Shiny is an incredibly powerful tool, it does come with its challenges and limitations:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Performance: Heavy computational tasks can slow down your app, affecting user experience.</p></li>
<li><p>Scalability: Shiny apps can require significant resources for multiple users, which can be a challenge for large-scale applications.</p></li>
<li><p>Learning Curve: For those unfamiliar with web development concepts, there might be a learning curve.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion:</h2>
<p>R Shiny offers a bridge between data analysis in R and interactive web applications, empowering data scientists to share their insights in a more dynamic and accessible way. Despite its challenges, the benefits of creating interactive and user-friendly applications make R Shiny a valuable tool in the data scientist’s toolkit.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>arewads</category>
  <category>shiny</category>
  <category>rprogramming</category>
  <guid>https://lukmanaj.github.io/ailearningloop/posts/first-shiny/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
